<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poor-mans physician and chyrurgion, containing above three hundred rare and choice receipts, for the cure of all distempers, both inward and outward: together with necessary considerations before purgation; easie rules for the opening of a vein, and the manner of bleeding by horse-leeches, with a method for drawing teeth. All being of great worth, and now published for the publique good: / by Lancelot Coelson student in Physick and Astrology.</title>
            <author>Coelson, Lancelot, 1627-ca 1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1666_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867347</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867347</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 209:E1666[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poor-mans physician and chyrurgion, containing above three hundred rare and choice receipts, for the cure of all distempers, both inward and outward: together with necessary considerations before purgation; easie rules for the opening of a vein, and the manner of bleeding by horse-leeches, with a method for drawing teeth. All being of great worth, and now published for the publique good: / by Lancelot Coelson student in Physick and Astrology.</title>
                  <author>Coelson, Lancelot, 1627-ca 1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Simon Miller at the Starre in St Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "17 June.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dentistry --  Practice --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE POOR-MANS PHYSICIAN AND Chyrurgion, CONTAINING Above Three hundred rare and Choice Receipts, for the Cure of all Diſtempers, both Inward and Outward: Together with neceſſary Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before Purgation; Eaſie Rules for the opening of a Vein, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Bleeding by Horſe-leeches, with a Method for drawing Teeth.</p>
            <p>All being of great Worth, and now Publiſhed for the Publique good:</p>
            <p>By LANCELOT COELSON Student in Phyſick and Aſtrology.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Simon Miller</hi> at the Starre in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1656.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119654:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119654:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Sir</hi> John Barkstead <hi>Knight, Lieutenant of the Tower of LONDON, High-Steward of COLCHESTER, Major General of MIDDLESEX and WESTMINSTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>L. C.</hi> wiſheth all Health, with long Life and Increaſe of Honour.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or many ages past it hath been a cuſtome amongst theſe who have endeavoured to leave to poſterity any of their Labours, to Dedicate them to ſome eminent
<pb facs="tcp:119654:3"/> Perſonage, partly to expreſſe their grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for benefits received, and partly to procure with the Readers a more eaſie acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation of the Work, and a more firm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection for it from the reproachfull tongues of malicious cenſures which no age hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ever wanted. Among the ſage ſayings of <hi>Solon,</hi> being an ancient Philoſopher of <hi>Athens,</hi> this is continually to be born in minde, that he only did glory of the good he received by his endeavours and ſtudy; the which Philoſopher was a Heathen man: I would we Chriſtians could follow the like example, but I fear moſt in our age neither return thanks for what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor apply themſelves to ſtudy any good, nay rather, there be ſome will ſpeak evil of them which apply their ſtudy to the knowledge of their Profeſsion, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Profeſſours of Arts. But in part being ſenſible of Your Honours inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, and ſo much a friend and lover of Vertue and Learning, I did make this bold attempt, which I hope Your Wiſdome will be pleaſed to pardon, this did the more
<pb facs="tcp:119654:3"/> encourage me to enterpriſe it. For I do ingeniouſly confeſſe that I have not thought this Labour of mine fit or worthy to be peruſed of Your Honour, by reaſon of my own inability, who am altogether inſufficient to perform any thing ſuitable to the acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance of Your Honour. It was not the affectation of any popular praiſe, but an honeſt zeal to benefit my Country, which begot in me a deſire to publiſh this Work; and in the next place I perceived in my ſelf a certain earnest willingneſſe which I have alway had to commend ſome piece of ſervice to Your Honour, this meeting together did induce me and re-inforce my over-preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous determination with ſuch a bold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, as it were, to ruſh into Your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and to demand, without any ſhew of merit, Your Honours moſt favourable Protection, that this Book of my Labours may runne under Your Patronage. The Lord God, who hath made Your Honour an Instrument to work the advancement of his Glory, the furtherance and propagation
<pb facs="tcp:119654:4"/> of good Learning, protect, guide and bleſſe You with all ſucceſſe in this world, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe in his Kingdom.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble Servant,</hi> Lancelot Coelſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119654:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen God had perfected that wonderfull work of his, I mean the frame of the World, and had aſſigned to every part thereof his ſpeciall duty, as namely to the water to harbour fiſhes, to the ayr to uphold all feathered fowls, to the earth to ſofter beaſts, and to produce and bring forth good and wholſome herbs and trees, and over all theſe, as Regent and Governour, had appointed man, his laſt and nobleſt creature, he demanded of his Angels, who were preſent with him at this work, what might be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this ſo rare and ſtrange a workmanſhip; who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Nothing but a tongue to unfold the ſecrets of his Labours, to talk and commune with them; with the which alſo, He as a Workman of all, might be extolled and magnified, there being no better way to advance his glory: As he did infuſe into man a conceivable minde apt to underſtand his myſteries, ſo now he gave him a tongue to utter what the minde was capable to receive; and it hath been the delight of many of our Anceſtours to give themſelves to ſtudy this noble Art of Phyſick and Chyrurgery, not only to ſtudy them, but to practiſe them for the good of themſelves and others: and not
<pb facs="tcp:119654:5"/> only ſo, but have ſpread their Labours and Knowledge over the whole world, knowing that what they had was nothing but what they had received, and not only for themſelves, but for the good of their Country.</p>
            <p>But we will remember ſome of thoſe Kings, who had an eſpeciall fantaſie to this Art, whoſe names are devol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and brought unto us by the ſucceſſion of ages, though their Works have not eſcaped the wrack, but have periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Sea-gulf of Antiquity, which have ſwallowed the good actions of many: And <hi>Mithridates</hi> the King of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontus</hi> ſhall be the firſt, whoſe glory in battell, being victorious, did much fore-paſſe all other, and yet gave his minde much to ſtudy the Book of the creature. In ſo much, as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liny</hi> remembereth, was alike profitable to the Commonwealth, and to mans life: For in his Mannor where he lay there were found many Books written by his own hands, both of the vertues of Herbs, and of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of mans Body, with remedies for many infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the ſame. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ax</hi> alſo the King of <hi>Arabia</hi> wrote a Book of the effects of Simples, which he Dedicated to <hi>Nero</hi> the Emperour. I need not mention them in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, there was no King either of <hi>Ethiopia, Aegypt</hi> or <hi>Arabia,</hi> who did not himſelf either write ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Art of Phyſick, or elſe by his liberality en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged others to imploy their time in the ſame.</p>
            <p>I will not ſtand to recite any of our famous Phyſicians who have lived before us in ſeverall ages, as <hi>Dioſcorides, Galen, Paulus Aetius, Egyneta,</hi> and others: For it will eaſily appear of what credit this Noble Science of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick was in times paſt, the inſolency and pride of which Phyſicians was ſo high, that many of them diſdained the fellowſhip of Kings, and expected homage as Gods. The opinion of this Science did ſo poſſeſſe the mindes of the people in thoſe daies, that they imagined the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of the ſame immediatly to be ſent from heaven, for
<pb facs="tcp:119654:5"/> the commodity of the whole Countrey, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of man-kinde, which begot in thoſe Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſuch a ſpirit of pride, expecting much reverence. I deſire the Phyſicians of our times may have contrary ſpirits, humble, meek and lowly, viſiting even the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Patients when help is required, for the life of the moſt miſerable vaſſal is as dear in the ſight of God, as the life of the moſt renowned Monarch; they glorifie God in ſo doing, ſerve their Country, and gain much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. For it is not enough for a Phyſician to know the conſtitution of the body, the diverſity of temperatures, the variety of diſeaſes, the cauſes, ſignes and ſymptoms of the ſame: but by knowing theſe things, and doing good to your Country, you gain much experience, at leaſt you finde many times diſeaſes to deal withall which <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> did never dream of, even ſuch diſeaſes as make many Phyſicians amazed, and to judge that their Art is unper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. If then it be ſo that Art is weak without practice, and that as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith, Experience is gotten <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ongo rerum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſu,</hi> let our Phyſicians not minde gain and ſelf intereſt more then to be harboured under the roof of the pooreſt vaſſal in the world, and ſeeing there is nothing given unto us of God, more acceptable then the health of the body, how honourably muſt we think of the means by which it is continued and reſtored, if loſt. <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> the King of <hi>Epire</hi> did ſacrifice unto no other God or Goddeſs but only unto health, to whom he erected a famous Temple in his own Country, calling it <hi>Templum Sanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> He craved nothing at the hands of his Gods but the fruition of his health, when going to battel againſt his enemies; thinking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat induſtry and diligence meeting with the health of the body, were able to atchieve any thing, were i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beſet with never ſo many dangers. Then Courteous Reader, the health of the body deſerving ſo much to be eſteemed, and the means ſo honourable by
<pb facs="tcp:119654:6"/> which it is preſerved and reſtored, if loſt; and truly the ignorance of my Country ſo much abounding, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect enemies to the health of their own bodies, I may compare them to thoſe people of whom God complaineth in another caſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 12, 13. which did not regard the works of the Lord, neither conſidered they the operation of his hands; therefore were they gone into Captivity, becauſe they wanted knowledge: But ſee what God ſaith of them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>They are wiſe to do evil, but to do good they have no knowledge,</hi> and for want of knowledge they are deſtroyed. See <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4 6. there being too too many ſuch perſons now living in this age have been arguments to provoke me to put this ſmall book forth to the view of the world, which I really intend for the publique good; I do deſire both the Learned and unlearned to take view thereof, I have endeavoured to give language ſuitable to both their capacities, expecting and deſiring the kinde acceptance of both, reſolving if God ſhall be pleaſed to preſerve life and health, not to let my pen reſt, but I will endeavour ſtill further to ſerve you to my power,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London, Eaſt Smithfield,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 25. 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>LANCELOT COELSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119654:6"/>
            <head>A Table of the Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ches. Page 36, 38, 39, 118.</item>
               <item>Ach or Ague. 40</item>
               <item>Aches or Bruiſes. 37</item>
               <item>Appetite loſt. 45</item>
               <item>Ague, an excellent Remedy. 41, 42, 43, 44</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>BAck. 46, 51, 62, 63, 155</item>
               <item>Belly bound. 46</item>
               <item>Biting of a mad dog. 72</item>
               <item>Bruiſes. 49, 50, 55, 115</item>
               <item>Bruiſe or Cut. 49</item>
               <item>Breath ſtinking. 53</item>
               <item>Bleeding to ſtop. 51</item>
               <item>Broken bones. 53</item>
               <item>Broken veins. 55</item>
               <item>Blood ſtaunching. 48, 56, 62</item>
               <item>Breaſt ſore. 54</item>
               <item>Burn or ſcald. 56</item>
               <item>Burning with gun-powder. 61</item>
               <item>Balſom Lucatella. 57</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119654:7"/>
               <item>Black plaiſter. 60, 142</item>
               <item>Bone mortified. 63, 64</item>
               <item>Breaſt diſeaſed. 65</item>
               <item>Bruiſes or Ach. 117</item>
               <item>Bloody Flux. 47</item>
               <item>Balſom rare. 183</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>CAnker. 71, 112, 113</item>
               <item>Chin-cough. 65</item>
               <item>Child-birth. 50</item>
               <item>Choller. 67</item>
               <item>Chollick and ſtone. 68, 69</item>
               <item>Chollick. 72</item>
               <item>Conſumption. 70, 72</item>
               <item>Corrupt Coar. 71</item>
               <item>Corns. 67</item>
               <item>Cough. 69, 105</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>DEafneſs. 75</item>
               <item>Diet-drink. 73</item>
               <item>Digeſtion. 75, 80</item>
               <item>Dropſie. 74, 76, 77, 78, 79</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>EYes ſore. 81, 82, 83</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119654:7"/>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>FAlling ſickneſs. 93</item>
               <item>Feavers. 144</item>
               <item>Fiſtula. 88, 93</item>
               <item>Fleam. 86, 87</item>
               <item>Flower of Oyntment. 119</item>
               <item>Flux of blood. 87, 95</item>
               <item>Flux. 92</item>
               <item>Fracture in Scull. 96</item>
               <item>French Pox. 123, 124, 150</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>GOut. 93, 94, 116</item>
               <item>Green ſickneſs. 146, 147</item>
               <item>Green wound.154, 155, 157</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>HEad. 157</item>
               <item>Head-ach. 97, 98, 99, 100</item>
               <item>Heat in face. 96</item>
               <item>Heart-burning. 98</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>JAundies. 101, 102, 104</item>
               <item>Impoſthume. 80, 102, 103, 144</item>
               <item>Itch. 101, 102, 103</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119654:8"/>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>KIngs-Evil. 104</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>LEgs ſore. 106</item>
               <item>Liver heat. 106, 107, 108</item>
               <item>Lungs. 53, 105</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>MAtrix. 111</item>
               <item>Menſtrues. 86, 114</item>
               <item>Milk to increaſe. 112</item>
               <item>Molten. 110</item>
               <item>Morphew. 110</item>
               <item>Mother. 111</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>N<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbneſs, 40, 114</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>PAlſie. 121, 131</item>
               <item>Pipes to open. 66, 120</item>
               <item>Plaiſter. 91</item>
               <item>Plague. 121, 122, 126, 127</item>
               <item>Pluriſie. 123, 127</item>
               <item>Preparative. 129</item>
               <item>Purges. 125, 126, 129, 130, 131, 132</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119654:8"/>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>REins running. 95, 134, 135, 136</item>
               <item>Rickets. 133</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>SAlve rare. 136, 139, 153</item>
               <item>Sear-cloth rare. 140, 142</item>
               <item>Sear-cloth. 154</item>
               <item>Sciatica. 41, 116, 140, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7</item>
               <item>Scurvy the cure. 146</item>
               <item>Sinews ſhrunk. 146</item>
               <item>Skull. 145</item>
               <item>Sleep to provoke. 136, 138, 144</item>
               <item>Smal Pox. 125</item>
               <item>Soars. 140, 149</item>
               <item>Speaking in ſleep. 139</item>
               <item>Spleen. 138, 139</item>
               <item>Stitch in the ſide. 137, 144</item>
               <item>Stone. 47, 136, 144</item>
               <item>Stomack weak. 62</item>
               <item>Strain to cure. 143</item>
               <item>Swelling. 147</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>TEeth. 150</item>
               <item>Tiſick. 148</item>
               <item>Tooth-ach. 45, 150</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119654:9"/>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>VEnome. 54</item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers. 156</item>
               <item>Vomiting to ſtay. 151, 152</item>
               <item>Vomiting to cauſe. 151</item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine to provoke. 152, 153</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>WAter to ſerindge. 152</item>
               <item>Weakneſs. 154</item>
               <item>Winde. 148, 157</item>
               <item>Women in Travel. 158</item>
               <item>Worms. 156, 197</item>
               <item>Wounds. 119, 158</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 77. <hi>line</hi> 14. <hi>adde</hi> the doſe one dram. <hi>p.</hi> 96. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>reade</hi> heat. <hi>p.</hi> 103. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>r.</hi> Corall. <hi>p.</hi> 107. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> no blood. <hi>p.</hi> 134. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>r.</hi> Dealthee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="instructions">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119654:9"/>
               <head>INSTRUCTIONS to be Obſerved in Phyſick &amp; Chyrurgery.</head>
               <head type="sub">When you enter upon the Cure of any Diſeaſe, let this be your Method.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>EE what ſuperfluous humor doth abound, that have reſpect to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Vomit or Purge, with a meet Medicine for it.</p>
               <p>As if Fleam abound, it muſt be holpen with ſuch a Medicine which expels Fleam.</p>
               <p>And ſo if Choler abound, or Melancholy, the ſame muſt be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe if the diſtemperature of the Liver or Spleen do weaken the Stomack, then the cure conſiſteth only in the healing of thoſe members, and not to adminiſter any thing for the Stomack at all.</p>
               <p>And let not any man ground himſelf only in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119654:10"/> the knowledge of an Urine, in the diſtinguiſhing between the Diſeaſe and the Cauſe thereof; as namely the Ague, or Cholick, or Flux, and ſuch like, and ſo to miniſter Means or Medicine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording.</p>
               <p>But let him ſearch out, if by all means poſſible, the cauſe it ſelf.</p>
               <p>For in all inward Diſeaſes there ought to be as much care taken of the pulſes, and of the State, and of the Diſpoſition of the Brain of him that is ſick, as of the Urine.</p>
               <p>Alſo the egeſtion, ſweat, and ſpittle, and other excrements, ought not to be neglected, for they may ſhew that which the Urine ſhew not.</p>
               <p>As for example, in a Pluriſie, or Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lungs, or in a Squinzy, or ſuch like, there is more known by the ſpittle, than there is by the Urine.</p>
               <p>And again in a Lask, or in a bloody Flux, or in a Chollick or Illiack, there is more certain judgment to be given by the egeſtion or ordure, than there is by the Urine.</p>
               <p>For Urine is nothing elſe but only the waſhy part of the blood, for it is ſeparated from the blood in the Liver, and ſucked from thence into the Reins, from whence it diſtilleth down into the bladder, and ſo paſſeth forth.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore that Urine is the excrement that is ſeparated from the blood, there is good
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119654:10"/> reaſon why it ſhould ſhew the ſtate of the Liver, and alſo of the blood in all parts of the body, and that it can declare the full ſtate of thoſe members which it paſſeth by, as of the Reins, the bladder, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>But certainly in other Diſeaſes that be out of the Veins, and be diſtant from the places by which the Urine paſſeth, there can be no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain judgement of the Urine, unleſs the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of the Diſeaſe have infected the blood or the liver in ſome ſort.</p>
               <p>This is the ignorance of many people, they think him worthy of no eſtimation that cannot at the firſt ſight of the Urine, judge whether it be a mans or a womans Urine, and how the Diſeaſe grieveth, and whether the party ſhall live or die, although it have been carried 20 or 30 miles, which is a thing unpoſſible to be known by the Urine.</p>
               <p>Therefore they that will take upon them to ſtudy Phyſick, let them well obſerve theſe four things following:</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſee the ſick perſons, and to confer with them about their grief, for none can ſo well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it as the party grieved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let them view and feel the pulſes of the ſick perſon, and obſerve well the ſtate of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let them view diligently all the excrements,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119654:11"/> not only the Urine, but alſo the Spittle, Sweat and Ordure.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, Conſider well where the grief is, and all the accidents that may happen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: Theſe things ought well to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all that ſtudy Phyſick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Next we will treat ſomewhat of the uſe of blood-letting, and the benefits that come thereby, and alſo the uſe and benefit of Purging, and I would wiſh all that ſtudy Phyſick and Chyrurgery to be carefull thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>FIrſt note, if the body do abound with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours which are ready to oppreſs nature, then whether there be any ſickneſs in the body at preſent, or danger of ſickneſs to enſue.</p>
               <p>Thoſe humours muſt be evacuated out of the body, either by Blood-letting, Purging, Vomit, Sweating, Bath, or elſe by ſome other evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But I will ſpeak only of evacuation by Blood letting and Purging.</p>
               <p>There be divers things to be conſidered of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore blood-letting.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The age of the patient.</item>
                  <item>2. The complexion.</item>
                  <item>3. The time of the year.</item>
                  <item>4. The region, the cuſtom, the ſtrength, and the vehemency of the Diſeaſe.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119654:11"/> 1. The age of children under 14 years of age, and aged perſons may not be let blood unleſs great neceſſity require it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The complexion ought to be noted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a hot complexion hath large Veins, and alway aboundeth with much blood, and they may therefore forbear a good quantity of blood.</p>
               <p>The cold complexion have narrow Veins, and little blood, and therefore their evacuation muſt be ſmall.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The time of the year muſt be conſidered, that the weather be not too hot, nor too cold, and therefore the Spring-time is moſt fit to let blood, becauſe then it is temperate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, Obſerve well the Region and Country, the cuſtom and ſtrength of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and the vehemency of the Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>A temperate Region is good to live in, where it is not too hot, nor too cold</p>
               <p>The cuſtom muſt be conſidered, for thoſe that uſe to bleed may better ſuffer it than thoſe that never were let blood.</p>
               <p>The ſtrength of the perſon muſt be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for if there be great weakneſs it is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to let blood at all, without neceſſity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
               <p>The vehemency of the Diſeaſe muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, for if the Diſeaſe be vehement, then you muſt not delay bleeding, if the former
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119654:12"/> circumſtances will permit.</p>
               <p>Then note alſo what ſign the Moon is in, you muſt take heed ſhe be not in a ſign that govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that member wherein you intend to open a Vein.</p>
               <p>And forſee that ſhe be in a ſign that is good to let blood in.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>For the Complexion, let blood</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">the</cell>
                        <cell role="label">The Moon being in</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Phlegmatick,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Aries</hi> or <hi>Sagittarius.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Melancholick,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Libra</hi> or <hi>Aquarius.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Cholerick,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Cancer</hi> or <hi>Piſses.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sanguine,</cell>
                        <cell>In either of theſe.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>For his Age, let blood</head>
                  <item>in his
<list>
                        <item>youth, from the change to the firſt quarter.</item>
                        <item>middle age, from the firſt quarter to the full.</item>
                        <item>elder age, from the full to the laſt quarter.</item>
                        <item>old age, from the laſt quarter to the change.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>For the time of the year, as I told you before, the Spring time is beſt, Harveſt indifferent.</head>
                  <item>let not blood
<list>
                        <item>the Moon in <hi>Taurus, Gem. Leo, Virgo,</hi> or <hi>Capr.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>the day before nor after the change &amp; full.</item>
                        <item>twelve hours before and after the quartils.</item>
                        <item>the Moon w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                           <hi>Jupiter</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> evil aſpected.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>For the time of the day, let blood</head>
                  <item>in the
<list>
                        <item>morning, after ſun-riſing, faſting.</item>
                        <item>afternoon, after perfect digeſtion, the air temperate, not South.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119654:12"/>
               <p> Notwithſtanding for the Phrenſie, the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, the Squinſie, the Pluriſie, the Apoplexy, a continuall Head-ach, growing of choler or blood, a hot burning Feaver, or any other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream pain, in this caſe a man may not tarry a choſen time, but incontinently with all ſpeed he is to ſeek remedy, but then you muſt not take away ſo great a quantity of blood, as at a choſen time might be expected.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Benefits that ariſe thereby.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. IT is a good remedy for all Diſeaſes that be ingendred of abundant flowing of eruption of blood, as be chiefly the Feavers called Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nochy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Alſo Phrenſie, Squinſie, Pluriſie, Perip-newmoney, Opthalmy, and all Inflammations and Impoſtimations, ingendred of blood in the Liver, the Spleen, the Reins, the Womb, the Shar, the Armholes, the Arms, the Legs, and to conclude, it is good to bleed for all Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, whether it be in the inward or outward parts of the body, or whether the grief is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or in danger ſhortly to ingender.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is alſo good in Feavers, whether they be continuall or intermittent, inſomuch that the obſtructions and ſtopings of the Veins be cauſed of immoderate reflection of the humors.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119654:13"/>
                  <p> Note alſo that blood-letting doth empty and evacuate from the body all humors alike, as well the good as the bad, and therefore ought to be uſed chiefly when there is a great abundance of blood in the body, and other humors.</p>
                  <p>Alſo it cauſeth nature to have the larger ſcope, and a free paſſing by opening and emptying of the ſtraight waies and paſſages of the Veins and Arteries.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. And laſtly, It being done in time, it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteth divers and ſundry Diſeaſes into which the body was both apt and ready to have fallen.</p>
                  <p>But ſee that none of thoſe things which are forbidden be in the way without great neceſſity, but then the common Proverb is, <hi>Neceſſitas non habet legem,</hi> neceſſity hath no Law.</p>
                  <p>Alſo let the party bleeding note, that after bleeding they walk not faſt, or that they do not uſe any vehement exerciſe, but let him be quiet and reſt himſelf till his ſpirits ſhall be well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed and quieted again.</p>
                  <p>Again let them not ſleep immediatly after it, and as I told you before, the time moſt fit to bleed is in the morning, for then every digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is perfectly finiſhed, and the ſuperfluities and excrements of each of them avoided out, which muſt be conſidered.</p>
                  <p>And thus have I treated concerning blood-letting, of the uſe and benefit thereof; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119654:13"/> now I do purpoſe to ſpeak ſomewhat of the uſe and commodity of purging.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Purging, and the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities that come thereby.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as it is neceſſary to be underſtood of all perſons, that every kinde of purgation hath that ſecret vertue and property in it ſelf, that when it is received into a mans body, and provoked to exerciſe its vertue that it hath by naturall heat labouring to digeſt it, then doth it draw unto it all ſuch humours as it hath vertue and power to purge.</p>
                  <p>And therefore a purgation is an evacuation of vicious and corrupt humours, which do often trouble and moleſt the body, but not of all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt humours alike.</p>
                  <p>For every purging Medicine doth draw unto it ſelf one peculiar and proper humour, that is either fleagm, choller or melancholly or watery humours.</p>
                  <p>And therefore perſons in health ought not to take a purgation, ſince they do not abound with corrupt humours.</p>
                  <p>For when the Medicine findeth no ſuch ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous humour as it hath vertue to draw, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth and waſteth the blood and the fleſh, and therefore age ought not to take purgations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119654:14"/> it waſteth, where there is not that abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it hath vertue to draw, and ſo it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous for age, and for thoſe that are in perfect health, which thing is alſo teſtified by <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> in the 37 Aphoriſme of his ſecond Book, where he ſaith after this ſort, <hi>Qui corpore benè ſe habent, hos purgare periculoſum eſt:</hi> That it is dangerous purging thoſe that are in perfect health.</p>
                  <p>And again, Becauſe every purging Medicine hath vertue to draw one peculiar humour, there ought good heed to be taken that ſuch a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine be miniſtred as hath vertue to draw out the humour abounding and no other, or elſe the not right adminiſtring of it may do much harm, and work many inconveniences to the body; and according to the ſaying of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in the laſt Aphoriſm of his firſt Book, in this manner, <hi>Si qualia oportet purgari purgentur, confert &amp; facilè ferunt difficulter:</hi> that is, If ſuch things be purged as ought to be, it profiteth, and may eaſily be ſuffered, but if the Medicine be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, it doth much harm and may not be born.</p>
                  <p>But alas the greateſt number of the common people do hold an opinion, that if they have a Medicine for a little money, which will provoke them often to ſtool, what humour ſoever it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, they perſwade themſelves they are ſafe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119654:14"/>
                  <p> But I would have theſe rules obſerved by all Phyſicians, before ſuch time as they miniſter any purgation which is before related.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Conſider the quantity and quality of the humour abounding, and the ſtrength of him or her that is ſick, the age and the time of the year, and the Diſeaſe, miniſter no purgations to thoſe which are weak and feeble, becauſe all manner of purgations do weaken nature.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Beware of ſtrong purgations, old people and children are not to receive a purgation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept great neceſſity.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Conſider the time of the year, and take notice that Summer-time, during the dog-daies, is not good to purge.</p>
                  <p>And alſo when the Sun is in <hi>Leo</hi> it is not good to purge, for then is nature burnt up, and made ſo weak withall, that ſhe is not able to ſuffer the violence of a purge, the Spring time is beſt, then it is temperate.</p>
                  <p>And again, the Phyſician ought to behold and contemplate the Diſeaſe, that ſo he knowing of what kinde it is, may the better finde out of what humour it is cauſed:</p>
                  <p>As for example, If he do perceive the Diſeaſe to be a Tertian Feaver, then ſtraitway he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that is cauſed of great abundance of choler, and therefore muſt of neceſſity miniſter a meet Medicine to purge choler, and ſo likewiſe in all Diſeaſes.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119654:15"/>
                  <p> Note alſo, that before a purgation be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred there ought to be a Medicine taken which ſhall prepare the body, and make it apt to purge, and therefore it is called a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
                  <p>It is given for two cauſes, either to divide, extenuate and make the groſs and clammy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, that they may be ready to flow out when the medicine draweth them; or elſe it is given to unſtop and open the conduits and veſſels of the body, by which the purgation muſt draw the ſuperfluous humours to it, and this is that which <hi>Hipocrates</hi> doth counſell in the firſt Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm of his ſecond Book, where he ſaith, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora cum quiſque purgare voluerit, oportet fluvia facere:</hi> that is, When a man would purge the body, he muſt make it flowing, by opening and unopening the veſſels.</p>
                  <p>There is good heed to be taken what ſign the Moon is in when you do adminiſter a purgation, for ſome ſigns are very good, other-ſome very ill, therefore I would adviſe all that ſtudy Phyſick to mark well all ſuch things before rehearſed, leaſt they do more hurt then good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">Good to</cell>
                           <cell role="label">the Moon in</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>prepare humours,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gem. Libra, Aquary.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Vomit,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aries, Taurus, Capri.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Purge by ſneezing,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Cancer, Leo, Virgo</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>take Clyſters,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aries, Libra, Scorpio.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>take Gargariſms,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Cancer</hi> or <hi>Aries.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>ſtop Rheums and Flux,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Taurus, Virgo, Capri.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>bath for cold Diſeaſes,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aries, Leo</hi> or <hi>Sagitary.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>bathe for hot Diſeaſes,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Cancer, Scorp.</hi> or <hi>Piſſes.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">Purge with</cell>
                           <cell role="label">the Moon in</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Electuary,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Cancer.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Potions,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Scorpio.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Pils,</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Piſſes.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119654:15"/>
                  <p>A purgation muſt alſo be taken hot, for ſo it offendeth the ſtomack leaſt, and it will work the ſooner and better.</p>
                  <p>And as for thoſe which are apt to Vomit, and are not able to bear ſmelling to a purgation, let them ſtop their noſtrils, or let them ſmell to ſome odoriferous thing, when they are about to take it.</p>
                  <p>And ſo ſoon as it is taken, it is good for the patient to ſmell to a toſt of brown bread dipped in Vineger, and to apply warm clothes to the ſtomack, and alſo to put the taſt of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine out of the mouth, with chewing ſome ſweet and pleaſant thing, and ſo by this means hinder Vomiting.</p>
                  <p>Note alſo that for the ſpace of an hour after that any purgation is taken, let the patient fit ſtill and be quiet, and in any caſe avoid ſleep
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119654:16"/> four or five hours, ſo that the ſtrength of the Medicine may the better paſs into all parts of the body, if it work but ſlowly let the patient walk up and down a good ſpace after.</p>
                  <p>And after the purgation hath done working, the patient muſt be nouriſhed with a mean quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of broth, and that will breed good juice, and be eaſily digeſted, and afterward by little and little return to his accuſtomed diet again.</p>
                  <p>Alſo note that there ought to be more care taken in miniſtring of all Potions, Electuaries and Pils, than in Clyſters and Suppoſitaries, by reaſon they enter no further then into the guts, where the ordure lieth, and by that place bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth the matter which cauſeth the Diſeaſe. But the other entereth into that way which both meats and drinks do come into the ſtomack, and there is boyled and ſent forth into the places of digeſtion, and afterward is mixed with the juice, whereof the ſubſtance of the body is made, and expelling the adverſe humours; yet ſome part thereof remaineth in the body, wherefore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ought to take heed and be carefull what Medicines they receive, that in them there be no venenoſity, malice or corruption, leaſt for the expelling of a ſuperfluous humour they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Medicine which ſhall ingender any ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous humour, and inevitable deſtruction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the whole body.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119654:16"/>
                  <p> And note alſo that after any purgation is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and hath wrought to full perfection, then thirſting and ſound ſleeping are good ſigns and tokens that the body is ſufficiently purged.</p>
                  <p>Having ſufficiently treated concerning the uſe of Blood-letting, and of Purgations, and the benefit coming thereby, I ſhall now in brief treat of the great neceſſity ſome people have to have their teeth drawn, and the benefit which comes thereby, and the manner how a Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhall behave himſelf to draw a tooth beſt for the eaſe of the patient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of drawing Teeth.</head>
                  <p>SOmetime it happeneth that there is great pain incident to Teeth, and ſuch torment that the party grieved is as Phrenſie that no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy can be found but drawing forth the Tooth.</p>
                  <p>Whenas therefore we would draw forth a Tooth, we muſt cauſe the Patient to ſit down in ſuch a place or ſort as is convenient, and then make choice of the corrupted or rotten Tooth, that we may not miſtake that from another, which we muſt make looſe from the gums, and fill up the concavity or hollowneſs of the Tooth with a little piece of lead, or a little lint or cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, filling it full, ſo as the pelicane chance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119654:17"/> not to break, thorow the hard ſhutting of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Having hold of it, we muſt eaſily and gently cruſh the inſtrument together, leſt the Tooth chance to break, and then drawing the foreſaid Tooth a little aſide, pluck it out, becauſe that if too rigorouſly we waggle the Tooth up or down, that part of the cheek bone wherein the Tooth ſtood might eaſily be broken, therefore it muſt not with too much violence be drawn. Another reaſon is, If it ſhould with violence be drawn out, it might disjoyn and pluck out of place the nethermoſt cheek-bone, and ſo cauſe great perturbation in the uppermoſt jaw, even to the eyes.</p>
                  <p>The Tooth being drawn we muſt with out finger joyn and ſhut together again the gums, and cauſe the Patient to waſh his mouth with a little excecrate, wherein we muſt put in a little ſalt, for if there be any efluxion of blood, it ought not to be eſteemed a ſmall thing; for I have known ſome to bleed even to death, and therefore the ſureſt way that ever I have known to be uſed is this, to thruſt therein ſome cotton which hath been madified in juice of Lemons, into that place from whence the Tooth was drawn.</p>
                  <p>Now having ſufficiently treated of that, I do next purpoſe to diſcourſe of the manner
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119654:17"/> how to open a Vein, or Phlebotomize.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Phlebotomy.</head>
                  <p>MY purpoſe and meaning is not now to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe unto you what Diſeaſe or Sickneſs requireth Phlebotomy, or what age, in what time or ſeaſon of the year, in what Countrey, in what conſtitution of the body it muſt be done, or of any particular occaſion:</p>
                  <p>But my purpoſe is only to ſhew you how you ought to open a Vein, and whereon we muſt diligently conſider before we make the apertion therein after we have opened it; and alſo where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we ought not, when the blood iſſueth forth out of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>For it is difficult and dangerous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is he praiſe-worthy that can bleed aright.</p>
                  <p>It is dangerous, becauſe the Veins are ſituated ſometimes cloſe to the Arteries, as are the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news and Tendons, that if we chance to hurt a Tendon with the Lancet, thereafter moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly iſſueth a <hi>Spaſmus</hi> or a Gangrene and mortification, and with great torment endeth his life.</p>
                  <p>If there be any Artery touched or opened, there will be great difficulty in curing of it, whereby the Patient may bleed to death, and whenas we deſcide a Vein quite aſunder, both
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119654:18"/> the ends thereof are immediatly retracted and drawn inward, the one end one way, and the other end the other way, ſo that under the fleſh both the ends are left, and no blood can poſſibly iſſue thereout.</p>
                  <p>If it be then with too great timerouſneſs and fear pricked, and the skin only wherewith it is covered, is as then inſcided, and the Vein not opened; or elſe if it be only pricked with the point of the Lancet, the blood as then iſſueth out droping-wiſe, and the ſubtleſt blood only cometh out, where conſequently thereafter it exulcerateth.</p>
                  <p>Sometime again the Vein lieth occultated ſo deep in the fleſh, that we cannot with the Lancet finde it without great pains.</p>
                  <p>Yea alſo, and although we eſpy them, yet through perpuſillity and rotundity they avoid and eſchew the point of the Lancet, how acute and ſubtle ſoever the ſame be, ſo that there are divers occaſions wherefore Phlebotomy is diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, which to one that hath never uſed it, it ſeemeth to be very eaſie.</p>
                  <p>But before the Chyrurgion maketh his aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Vein, if ſo be the Patient be reſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and bound in his belly, and have not in a long time been at ſtool.</p>
                  <p>We muſt firſt of all cauſe him to uſe a Clyſter, becauſe through the Phlebotomy the Veins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119654:18"/> evacuated and emptied, do not atract and draw unto them out of the guts or entrails, any corrupted or rotten humours whereby any of the worthieſt parts might be offended and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Conſider whereon we ought to be well adviſed before we Phlebotomize.</head>
                  <p>PHlebotomy is not expedient, when as the ſtomack is burthened either with any crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of undigeſted meat or drink, or with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſcoſity whatſoever, and alſo it is wholly diſſwaded to be done after any great evacuation or any other occaſion whereby the Patient might be debilitated, as is the ſuperfluous breaking a great lask, great abſtinence, continuall vigila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and great converſation of women, and when all theſe things are conſidered, then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
                  <p>If any perſon ſhall deſire to be Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miz'd to prevent any Diſeaſe, he muſt then cauſe it to be done when he is beſt of courage, as being freed from ſorrow.</p>
                  <p>And beſide we muſt not Phlebotomize any perſon which is fearfull and timorous to bleed, becauſe then the fear cauſeth the blood to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw it ſelf toward the internall parts of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119654:19"/>
                  <head>Conſider alſo how we ſhould conveniently Phlebotomize.</head>
                  <p>THe Patient being luſty and ſtrong, we muſt then cauſe him to ſit in a ſtool, but if he be feeble, and ſubject unto faintneſs and ſwouning, as thoſe be which are of a hot nature, then we muſt firſt let him ſip in a ſoft-dreſſed egg, or a morſell of bread ſopped in wine, and then cauſe him to lie on a bed half ſetting upright, and ſtuff him under with cuſhions, as if he ſate.</p>
                  <p>And above all note that the light of the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or of the air do rightly ſhine on the Vein, becauſe that through the ſhadow thereof the knowledge of the Vein and of the place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it muſt be pierced be not vaniſhed out of your ſight.</p>
                  <p>Then muſt the Chyrurgion with his right hand take the right hand of the Patient, or with his left hand the left hand of the Patient, out of which he meaneth to draw blood, depreſſing the arm ſomewhat downward, and with his hand which is free from holding the hand of the Patient, or with a warmed napkin rub the inſide of the arm where he intendeth to make the aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then binde the arm double a little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the elbow, with a little narrow liſt or ſilk, not too ſtiff, nor too looſe, becauſe too looſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119654:19"/> or too ſtiff binding do both of them hinder bleeding.</p>
                  <p>Then muſt the Patient ſhut his hand, ſo that the Veins lie faſt and ſtedfaſtly in the fleſh and not move this way or that way, and then they alſo raiſe themſelves and ſwell the more, by the which we may the eaſier ſee and feel them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How we ought conveniently to make an apertion in the Vein.</head>
                  <p>IF the Chyrurgion determine to Phlebotomize in the right arm, he muſt then lay hold on the ſaid arm with his left hand, by the bending of the arm, or about that place where we purpoſe to make the apertion, and lay his thumb on the Vein a little below the place where he would prick, that ſo he may hold the Vein ſtedfaſt without gliding this way or that way, becauſe ſometime the Vein ſpaimed like a little cord, may chance to rowl and glide under the Lancet, and becauſe the aforeſaid Vein is oftentime empleat with wind and ventoſities, it therefore yieldeth and ſlideth away under the Lancet, where through we cannot fully pierce it, and by this means the apertion-Vein falleth too ſmall.</p>
                  <p>All this being in this ſort noted, we muſt with the firſt finger of the right hand feel where with moſt convenience we might make the apertion, ſetting an impreſſion on the skin above the Vein
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119654:20"/> where you purpoſe to prick with the nail of your finger, and then immediatly take the Lancet in the right hand, which between our lips we muſt have in a readineſs, with the which we finely muſt make our apertion in the Vein cauſing the point and accuity of the ſame gently to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the concavity of the Vein, and not abruptly and rudely with a haſty thruſt.</p>
                  <p>And to make this apertion the more certain and without trembling of the hands, the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion muſt take the Lancet in the middle with his thumb and his firſt finger, ſuffering his hand with three of his fingers to reſt on the arm, and ſo lay his thumb and his firſt finger which hold the Lancet, on the thumb which holdeth faſt the Vein, and ſo without any tremefaction to uſe the ſame.</p>
                  <p>If that the apertion be made at one thruſt, it is good, but if not you muſt immediatly give another prick, either a little below the ſame, or a little above it, if the Vein ſufficiently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth her ſelf.</p>
                  <p>And when you have made the apertion, and it prove too ſmall that the blood iſſue out of the ſame too ſubtilly, ſo that you fear you ſhall not draw blood enough thereout, then immediatly we muſt thruſt into the ſame apertion again and a little dilute the ſame, becauſe that oftentimes through too ſmall an apertion the groſs blood
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119654:20"/> congealeth before the apertion, and then conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently it exulcerateth.</p>
                  <p>Having conveniently made or brought to paſs this apertion, we muſt then give the Patient in the hand of that arm whereon he is Phlebotomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, a round ſtaff thereon to reſt his arm, as alſo to turn round the aforeſaid ſtaff in his hand, that by that means the blood may the better iſſue out, which if it do not iſſue out aright, we muſt then mark if the ligature be not the cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as if it were too hard tied, then we muſt a little diſtrict and make it looſe, without wholly looſing of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>A Chyrurgion muſt alſo have divers Lancets, whereof the one muſt be a little broader then the other: The broad Lancets are very neceſſary when the Veins lie high exalted, and when we deſire to make an ample apertion.</p>
                  <p>The ſmall narrow Lancets are very neceſſary, when as the Veins lie profoundly occulted in the fleſh, and alſo when as in the high exalted Vein we deſire to make a ſmall apertion, becauſe ſometime the Patient requireth a great and feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Phlebotomy, to the which end we muſt make an ample apertion, as we muſt alſo do if we conjecture the blood to be groſs, and when the Patient is luſty and ſtrong. And contrarily if ſo be we retract and draw back the blood which ſupernaturally hath iſſued out of any part
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119654:21"/> of the body, as in thoſe which ſpit blood, or thoſe which bleed much at the noſe. As then we muſt make our apertion ſmall, by reaſon great evacuation of blood is not neceſſary for them, becauſe through their noſes they have avoided ſufficient, then only in ſuch accidents is required a regreſſion of blood.</p>
                  <p>And beſides it is neceſſary that in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid evacuation and ſickneſs we ſuffer the blood to run out long enough out of the apertion of the Vein, which the Patient would not be able to endure if the aforeſaid apertion were ample, becauſe there would iſſue too much blood other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies thereout.</p>
                  <p>We are alſo in Phlebotomy urged to make a ſmall apertion in thoſe which are troubled with the frenſie, and in thoſe which are grown mad, becauſe that a little wound might with all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be cured again.</p>
                  <p>For ſuch frantick perſons will alway make looſe the ligature or dreſſing before we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thereof, and ſo they might come in danger of bleeding to death.</p>
                  <p>But the apertion being ſmall, although they looſen the arm, yet notwithſtanding they cannot bleed violently, becauſe in ſuch a ſmall apertion the blood congealeth and ſtoppeth the wound.</p>
                  <p>We ought in ſmall Veins to make a ſmall aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in great Veins an ample apertion:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119654:21"/> For if ſo be we make a ſmall apertion in a great Vein, then will neceſſarily follow that the blood which coagulateth in the ſmall Veins, be a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance unto the iſſuing or running out of the blood.</p>
                  <p>Touching the form and figure of the inciſion, it is effected three ſundry ſorts and faſhions.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is made overthwart.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond to the length of the Vein, ſo that the Vein is cleft or ſplit and not pricked.</p>
                  <p>The third is a mean between them both which we may properly call the contradictory aperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe ſo it is made.</p>
                  <p>We make the apertion overthwart when we are minded to reiterate the Phlebotomy, for when we bend the arm or elbow, then both the ends of the Vein joyn together again; this figure or form is very neceſſary when as we deſire to make a large apertion.</p>
                  <p>We muſt make the apertion ſidelong or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory, when we purpoſe to iterate the Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy, and we making the apertion in this manner, very ſeldom or never miſs the Vein, and it is better for the circumſtances and ſtanders by when the blood iſſueth out.</p>
                  <p>That inciſion which is made according to the length of the Vein is very expedient when we intend to renew the blood-letting, and that not only upon the ſame day, but on the next day
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119654:22"/> alſo, becauſe that when we bend the elbow, both the <hi>labia</hi> or lips of the Vein do ſeparate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide themſelves.</p>
                  <p>But in what form ſoever we make the inciſion, yet notwithſtanding the Vein muſt be pierced in the middle without wholly cutting aſunder of the ſame, becauſe the lips of the Vein might chance to be inverted inwards, and then the blood cannot reſult out of the apertion, but run downwards along by the arm, or both the ends of the Vein may be drawn inwards without deliverance of any blood from it, or at leaſt in the firſt very little.</p>
                  <p>This is not enough neither, but we muſt well obſerve this method after the thruſt and apertion is made in the Vein, and when the blood iſſueth thereout.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall know when the Vein moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is well opened, when as in the firſt the blood ruſheth, and as it were, leapeth out in great haſte, but many times through the affrighting of the Patient, it immediatly altereth unto drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the reaſon is becauſe then the blood is drawn inwards.</p>
                  <p>When this chanceth at any time unto us, we muſt with patience abide, and ſomewhat unbinde it, and encourage the Patient, cauſing him to move his fingers and to turn and cruſh the ſtaff in his hand.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119654:22"/>
                  <p> Sometimes the apertion in the Vein is ample enough, but becauſe the blood is groſs it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not iſſue thereout, and for that purpoſe it is good to put in a little oyl into the apertion to make the blood iſſue forth. And if the Patient be weak and feeble it is not good to draw too much blood at once, but rather to renew the Phlebotomy the ſecond time certain hours after, nay if need require the third time, rather then to over-charge the Patient with too great a Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy at one time.</p>
                  <p>The Chyrurgion muſt not in ſuch a caſe alway follow the advice of the Phyſician.</p>
                  <p>For it might chance that before we could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſuch a quantity of blood as the Phyſician did ordain, the Patient might chance to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitated and in danger to fall into great faintneſs and ſwouning, whereon the Chyrurgion muſt well conſider.</p>
                  <p>This you may eaſily perceive when the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent waxeth pale and oppreſſed at his heart, his pulſe diminiſhing, and when the blood runneth down by his arm.</p>
                  <p>When at any time this chanceth, the Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion muſt then immediatly ceaſe bleeding, laying his thumb upon the apertion of the Vein, and lay the Patient upon his back, with his head on a cuſhion, ſprinkling cold water on his face, and give him a little wine in his mouth, and cauſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119654:23"/> him to ſmell to ſome Vineger, and have a little patience till he reviveth and come to himſelf, for as ſoon as he ſhall come to his former ſtrength, we may then finiſh the Phlebotomy.</p>
                  <p>Some there are which in any ſort cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Phlebotomy how low ſoever they ſit, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be on a bed, or although you do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually hold Vineger before their noſe, or give them wine to drink, yet notwithſtanding let them lie proſtrate on the bed with their head reaſonable high, they can then very well en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and abide the aforeſaid Phlebotomy, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we draw a great quantity of blood from them.</p>
                  <p>After that we have detracted a reaſonable quantity of blood out, we muſt then diſſolve and make looſe the ligature, and cruſh out the blood of the Vein, leſt that the blood congeal therein and coagulate, and ſo exulcerate.</p>
                  <p>If there appeareth any little parcel of pingue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity or fat, we muſt then gently thruſt it in again with the head of a pin, and not cut it off, and then wipe away the blood that cleaveth and is dried or exciccated to the arm.</p>
                  <p>Then lay a little compreſe on the apertion which is madefied in cold water; and winde the lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>re twice or thrice about the elbow like a burgundian croſs, without tying both the ends faſt, before you have cauſed the Patient to bend
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119654:23"/> his arm to lay the ligature thereafter.</p>
                  <p>This ligature muſt not be too ſtiff bound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the cicatrice by that means may quickly be ſituated on the apertion of the Vein.</p>
                  <p>The arm being thus bound, if the Patient be able to walk he muſt wear his arm before on his breaſt in a ſcarf, and if he lieth on a bed he muſt gently lay the ſame beſide him without much moving of the aforeſaid arm, neither muſt he lie thereon, for ſome have in their ſleeps had their arm violently to bleed with great danger of their lives.</p>
                  <p>Blood iſſueth ſometimes ſo violently out of ſome parts of the body, that with no compreſe or ligature we can reſtrain the ſame.</p>
                  <p>When this happeneth we are then conſtrained to lay above on the top of the apertion, the one half of a green bean, and the compreſe thereon, and ſo bind it together.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes there remaineth a nigredity or blackneſs, and viridity or greenneſs about the apertion, but thereof enſueth no evil, unleſs any other accident chanceth thereunto.</p>
                  <p>When we do intend to renew the Phlebotomy, we muſt then lay on the inciſion ſalted oyl, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that hindreth the curing of the wound, and the ſalt keepeth the blood from coagulation, where-through the apertion of the wound is ſtopped.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119654:24"/>
                  <p> And if the wound were ſo ſtopped that the blood would hardly iſſue thereout, we muſt not then rigorouſly ſtretch out the arm which the Patient did carry on his breaſt doubled, neither muſt we depreſs the Vein with great violence to get the blood thereout, becauſe ſuch violence might cauſe great pain and inflammation: But we muſt rather with a ſmall prinet or ſearching iron, remove that blood which therein is excic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and dried, or rather once again make an inciſion.</p>
                  <p>When we deſire to make an apertion in the Veins or Arteries of the temples of the head, of the forehead, or under the tongue, we muſt then cauſe the Patient to wring about his neck a table napkin or a towell, thereby to cauſe the blood to aſcend on high, and the Veins to ſwell which we intend to open.</p>
                  <p>And when as we intend to open the Veins of the hands or feet, we muſt bathe them in warm water, becauſe through calidity and warmth of the water the aforeſaid Veins might erect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the blood Vein being opened, the blood may the better iſſue forth.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I as fully as may be given Rules of bleeding, and the uſe thereof, that a weak ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity may attain thereunto.</p>
                  <p>Some again there be which deſire bleeding with horſe-leeches, and that you may not be left
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119654:24"/> without the manner how to uſe them, obſerve theſe following Rules.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of bleeding by Horſe-leeches.</head>
                  <p>YOu may know them thus, they are little and perpuſill creatures like a worm, of the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude of a finger or thereabout, neither are they of any great craſſitude or thickneſs, unleſs it be when they are ſucking of blood.</p>
                  <p>The end of their head hath a round hole, much like unto a little lamprell, wherein are to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and ſeen three ſtings or acuities proceeding out of three corners, which ſo violently and ſtrongly prick, that therewith they can pierce the skins of all creatures, and thereon they will hang faſt untill ſuch time as they have ſucked themſelves round and full of blood of their own accord.</p>
                  <p>They live and are ingendred in the water, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in ſtanding waters, becauſe they delight and are ſolaced in all filthy and muddy places: I ſuppoſe there is no Chyrurgion but doth well know them, becauſe of all men they are known, but every man doth not know which are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous and which are not venomous, which is very neceſſary to be known, by reaſon of the many accidents and miſchances which might happen thereof.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119654:25"/>
                  <p> As for example great tumors, inflammations and venomous ulcerations, through their veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous momorſions and bitings, yea alſo and death it ſelf doth inſue: As for example, one was bitten on his knee by one that was venomous, and died thereof.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall know them by their greatneſs and colour, and by the place where they are caught.</p>
                  <p>For thoſe which are thick and have a head thicker then the reſt of their whole body, ſhining like unto gliſtering worms and are greeniſh and have on their back blew or black ſtrokes or lines, and were caught in ſtanding pools, where all manner of ſtinking carions and other filthineſs is thrown, they are all venomous, therefore in no caſe uſe them.</p>
                  <p>But thoſe which are ſmall, round, and have a little head, and are of colour much like unto a liver, a round belly, and the back ſtroaked with gold yellow ſtrokes, and live in clean running water, they are not venomous, but you may ſafely uſe them; yet not ſo ſoon as they are caught, but firſt of all keep them two or three weeks in a glaſs of fair water, becauſe therein they may void the viſcoſity and impureneſs.</p>
                  <p>And be ſure to refreſh the aforeſaid water every three daies, and waſh the ſaid horſe-leeches with your hand from all their filth and ſlimineſs.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119654:25"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Galen</hi> doth counſell the firſt day to keep them in blood, and then put them in freſh water, and thus we may preſerve them a whole year or longer if we pleaſe to uſe them when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
                  <p>The uſe of them was invented in ſtead of ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying, we may apply them on ſuch places of the body where we cannot ſet any boxes at all.</p>
                  <p>As for example, in the privities, on the gums, on the lips, and ſometime on the raw fleſh of any wound, or on the noſe, or above on the hand or fingers, or on the legs or thighes alſo.</p>
                  <p>And when the Patient feareth boxing, or elſe when we deſire to draw and extract any venom out of a thruſt or bite of any venomous creature, before we apply them, and becauſe they might be hungry and not to retain any thing in their bodies, and becauſe they ſhould the ſooner lay hold we muſt take them out of the water three or four daies before we uſe them, and put them in a little new box of wood, and keep them ſo till we uſe them.</p>
                  <p>We muſt firſt waſh that place where we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to apply them very clean, and if the place by reaſon of ſalve or plaiſter be faulty, you muſt waſh it off clean alſo, becauſe they are enemies unto all pinguedity and fatneſs: this being done, we muſt take them one after the other in their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119654:26"/> middles with a white clean cloth, for if we touch them with our bare fingers it will hinder their biting or placing their heads to that place where we would have them ſuck: if they will not at the firſt lay hold we muſt then anoint the place with pigeons or hens blood, or cauſe the place, either with the point of a Lancet, or with the point of a pin to bleed, and then immediatly ſhe will begin to ſuck.</p>
                  <p>And if ſhe do not ſuck ſo violently as we do deſire, or if we would have her ſuck more then ſhe is able to hold, we muſt then with a pair of ciſers clip her aſunder above the third part of the body, whereby ſhe will begin to ſuck farre ſtronger and with more violence, and as faſt as ſhe ſucketh the blood departeth from her through the hindermoſt parts which is cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
                  <p>If they be not cut when they have ſucked themſelves full they will fall off, and when one is fallen off, you may apply another on the ſame place, for when they are ſatisfied they will of themſelves fall off.</p>
                  <p>And if we would have them fall off before they are ſatisfied, we may then ſtrew a little ſalt or aſhes of wood, and they will immediatly fall off.</p>
                  <p>If when they are fallen off, blood doth drop from the bite, it is a ſign that they have drawn
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119654:26"/> blood from farre, which blood we muſt not on the ſudden ſtop, becauſe that part may be the better purged and purified from all venomous humours, if any be at hand.</p>
                  <p>For which cauſe ſome do apply ſmall boxes upon the place ſucked, or elſe they waſh that place with hot water being ſalted, and ſo cauſe it to bleed ſomewhat longer, if cauſe require, and the Patient be able to ſuffer it.</p>
                  <p>And if the blood runne out too long and will hardly be reſtrained through compreſe, we muſt then apply thereon a little aduſted or burned linnen with his finger, or a cloven bean, retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame with his finger ſo long thereon till he can come to lay on a ſmall compreſe and binde the ſame thereon, if poſſibly it may be done.</p>
                  <p>And ſo I have been as good as my word to give you the method of bleeding with Horſe-leeches.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="catalogue_of_medicines">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119654:27"/>
               <head>Here follows a Catalogue of ſuch Medicines as are good to Cure all or moſt Diſeaſes incident to Mans body, from the Head to the Foot, as well Inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Outwardly.</head>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent Medicine for that Grief we call an Ach in the Bones.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> Neats-foot oyl, Oxe gall, and oyl of Camomill it ſelf, and boyl them all together, and ſtirre it well untill it be well boyled and conſumed to a pint, then ſtrain it, and when you will uſe it anoint the place grieved therewith, and this will aſſwage the pain immediatly. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Scurvy-graſs, and put thereto a good quantity of Barrows-greaſe and ſtamp them together, and then boyl them together, and when it is well boyled then ſtrain forth the liquor into ſome Gallipot, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119654:27"/> ſtop it cloſe, and when you have an occaſion to uſe it anoint the place grieved often there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with before a good fire, and this will cure the Ach in a ſhort time. <hi>Prob. est.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a pint or ſomewhat more of good malmſie, one pint of Capons greaſe, and one penyworth of Frankincenſe finely beaten to powder and ſifted very fine, boyl all theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till one half be conſumed, and then ſtrain it, and ſo keep it cloſe for your uſe in ſome gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipot, and anoint the place grieved often there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with and it will help. <hi>Prob. est.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, although it be a Sciatica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Neats-foot oyl, and <hi>Aqua compoſita</hi> and mingle them both together, and let the Patient anoint the place where the pain is, and take new plucked wool from the ſheeps back and lay it upon the grief, and wrap it well with warm clothes, and this will help him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, and good for all manner of Aches and Bruiſes in the Bones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Wallwort, and a certain quantity of Balm and Smallidge and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119654:28"/> ſtamp them all together, then take a pound of <hi>May</hi> butter and temper them very well together, then make them up in round bals, and let them lie the ſpace of eight daies after, and then ſtamp them again as you did before, then take it and fry it and put it into an earthen diſh or pot and ſo uſe it, and this will help a bruiſe though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo black. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious Plaiſter for all manner of Aches, for as ſoon as the Plaiſter is warm on the fleſh the pain is gone, excellent for the Gout.</head>
                  <p>TAke unwrought wax two pound, Deer ſuet half a pound, perroſon four pound, mace and cloves of each two ounces and a half, ſaffron one ounce, roſin two pound, pitch four ounces, powder the Spices, and melt thoſe things which are to be melted, powder your ſaffron with the Spices and ſearce them, ſet your things which are to melt on a ſoft fire, and when it is boyling pour in by little and little at a time a pottle of red wine, ſtirring it well into the ſalve, and when it is well melted ſtrain it into a clean pan, and then put in your powder of Cloves, Mace, and Saffron, caſting it abroad upon your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients, ſtirring them well together, and let them ſtand till they be cold, then anoint your hands with oyl and greaſe, and while it is warm
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119654:28"/> make it up into good big rowls, draw it with your hands till it be coloured like wax, and wrap every rowl into a piece of oyled paper and keep it for your uſe. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent oyntment for all Aches, Rickets, Stich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, bruiſed Shoulders, and all Colds.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Sage and Rew of each one pound, of Wormwood and Bayleaves of each half a pound, one handfull of Roſemary, chop theſe herbs as ſmal as may be, adde thereunto the like weight of ſheeps ſuet clean picked from the skin and cut ſmal, bring theſe unto one ſubſtance, and adde thereunto oyl-olive a pottle and a pint, and work them together with your hands to one ſubſtance, then cover them cloſe that no ayr come to them for the ſpace of nine daies, then ſet it on a fire and boyl them ſoftly, alway ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them till the herbs be purged, then ſtrain them and keep them for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another moſt approved Medicine for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke half a pound of Mutton ſuet of the near, and one pint of white-wine Vineger, and one piece of roſell as big as an egge, and one handfull of Elder leaves, and one handfull of Camamill, and ſhred them very ſmall, and boyl
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119654:29"/> theſe altogether while they are boyl'd half away, and with this make a Plaiſter and lay to the grief and it will cure approvedly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious Oyntment good for the Ach in the Bones, or to take the Ague out of any part of the Body.</head>
                  <p>TAke Wormwood and Rue, Vervine, Dill, and herb <hi>John,</hi> and Balm, of each a like quantity cut them very ſmall, and then boyl them in Mutton ſuet and freſh <hi>May</hi> butter, of each a like quantity till it come to the ſubſtance of an oyntment, ſtrain it and keep it for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a quantity of Roſin and a quarter of a pound of Mutton ſuet, and a quantity of Bees wax, and a quantity of Saffron, and a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Boneſet, and a quantity of Roman nettles, and boyl them like a ſalve.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, or numbneſs in the Joynts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a linnen cloth and wet it in Dragon water and apply it very warm morning and evening, or drink ſix ſpoonfuls of Dragon wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and one dram of <hi>Methredatum</hi> three morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119654:29"/> together, and ſweat every morning two hours. Cureth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent for the ſame, or Sciatica, or to expell wind, or to eaſe pain in the Back or ſtone in the Kidneys, anoint the place therewith firſt rub it well with a dry cloth.</head>
                  <p>TAke an Oxe gall, flit it in the bottom, and let it run out into a pipkin, and adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one pound of Neats-foot oyl and ground Ivy, Rue, Camamill and Thyme, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, pound them in a mortar together, adde thereto one ounce of <hi>aqua vitae,</hi> boyl them all at a ſoft fire threequarters of an hour, ſtirre it often in the boyling, and then ſtrain it, and ſo it is made.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An excellent remedy for the cure of that Diſeaſe ſo hardly to be cured,</hi> viz. <hi>the Ague.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke two ounces of bay ſalt, and two ounces of Frankincenſe, and one handfull of Smal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidge, beat them together, and lay them to the wriſts of both your hands, and to the bows of your arms, let this be done two hours before the fit cometh. <hi>Prob eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119654:30"/>
                  <head>For a burning Ague.</head>
                  <p>TAke one handfull of Strawbery leaves, and one handfull of Violet leaves, one handfull of Sorrel leaves, and ſo ſtamp them and ſtrain them into poſſet-ale, and drink it as hot as you can ſuffer it when your fit is coming upon you. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent Medicine for an Ague or burning Fever: It hath cured ſome which were thought paſt cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke two handfuls of Plantine, and as much Ribleaf which is like Plantine but ſomewhat longer, a pottle of running water, but take it up againſt the ſtream, two penny worth of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoriſh fine ſcraped, and boyl them altogether till the liquor come to a pint, then put it into as much Sugar-candy as you think fit to ſweeten it, and then ſtrain it and let the Patient drink of this at all times, refuſing all other drink as near as he can till the Feaver leaveth him. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent for an Ague, bruiſe or ſprain.</head>
                  <p>TAke Rue, Yarrow, Dill, Self-heal, Vervain, Mugwort, Comfry, Adders tongue, red
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119654:30"/> Sage, Fennell, red Nettles, red Dock leaves, Valerian, <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> of each two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, bruiſe all theſe together in a mortar, and then boyl them in one pound and a half of <hi>May</hi> butter for a quarter of an hour ſtill ſtirring it, then ſtrain out the herbs, and add to the liquor oyl of Dill, and oyl of <hi>exceter,</hi> of each one dram, let them be ſet upon the fire again, and let it boyl one wallop, and when it is cold anoint the place grieved therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>The Ague fallen into the legs, which cauſe them to ſwell. The Cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Plantine, Marygold, Houndstongue, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi> wort, Bettony, red Fenill, Southiſtle, Dandelion, Smallidge, Plumtree leaves, of each of them a handfull, ſhred them ſmall, and adde to them wheat meal, and ſeeth them in hot Cows milk to a plaiſter, and ſo apply it, this will diſſolve the humour and digeſt it by the ſeroſity of the blood. Approved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Medicine to cure the Ague either in old or young.</head>
                  <p>TAke as much milk as will make you a quart of poſſet-ale, and then take the young tops of Roſemary, Marygolds, Plantine, and young
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119654:31"/> Bay leaves, of each two drams, cut them ſmall and boyl them in the poſſet-ale untill all the ſtrength be out, then drink a great draught thereof ever before the fit cometh, and ſweat upon it, do this three times and it will cure. Approved by many.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another approved Medicine for an Ague and Feaver.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke of Dragon water, and of <hi>aqua compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita</hi> to the quantity of a quarter of a pint of each, and put therein a pennyworth of <hi>London</hi> Treakle, and half a quarter of an ounce of groſs beaten Pepper, warm all theſe together and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtirring it with a knife, and give it the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to drink as hot as he may ſuffer it, a little before the fit cometh, and let him lie down and ſweat very well. This hath cured many.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke an Oxe-gall and as much <hi>aqua compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita,</hi> and put unto it a quarter of an ounce of pepper a little bruiſed, and adde to it two pennyworth of Treakle, and anoint the hands and wriſts and ſtomack with the things aforeſaid, being all mingled together, let this be done half an hour before the fit cometh, and applied
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119654:31"/> as hot as the Patient can ſuffer it, and let him ſweat well upon it and it will ſpeedily cure him. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent Plaiſter for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke red Roſe water, <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine and Frankincenſe, of each of them two pennyworth, and mingle them well together, then take a piece of white ſheeps leather ſit for both the wriſts and ſtrike the ſame upon them and apply them hot to both the wriſts of the party grieved, and let the ſame remain till it fall off of its own accord. This hath cured thoſe that have been troubled therewith two years, who have taken the diſeaſe in forreign Countries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the tooth-Ach.</head>
                  <p>TAke a little cotton and dip it in the eſſence of Cloves which you may have at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, and thruſt it into the hollowneſs of the tooth and it will appeaſe the pain preſently, and you will be well. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To cauſe a good Appetite.</head>
                  <p>TAke Centory and boyl it in fair water, and put into it one ounce of Sugar-candy, Sugar
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119654:32"/> and Anniſeeds, of each a like quantity, boyl theſe well together, and let the Patient drink thereof lukewarm every morning for ſix morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings together, three ſpoonfuls at a time, this will help although the party be never ſo farre ſpent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Plaiſter to eaſe pain or a crick in the Back.</head>
                  <p>TAke white Archangell flowers and leaves a good quantity, and of Comfry leaves and roots of Plantine one ounce, <hi>burſa paſtoris</hi> one ounce, beat them altogether very well, and put unto them a ſpoonfull of honey, and fry them in a pan, and divide it into four parts, and make of every part a Plaiſter, and lay it on the back of the Patient in four nights when he goeth to bed. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Remedy for one that is Bound in his Belly.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Hempſeed and ſeeth it in fair running water, and then ſtrain it through a fair linnen cloth, and let the Patient drink a good draught when he goeth to bed, and it will make him laxitive.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119654:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a chicken, and a pretty quantity of <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſula fuſtula</hi> and ſeeth them together in fair running water, and let the Patient drink the broth and it will make him laxitive without pain.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A marvellous good Water to break the ſtone in the Bladder.</head>
                  <p>TAke two pints of the juice of Saxifrage, the juice of Gromell, and of the juice of Parſly, each of them a pint, and put thereto a quantity of eight or nine ounces of the beſt Vineger that is made of pleaſant Wine, and diſtill all theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and then put the diſtilled water into ſome glaſs or other veſſel with a narrow mouth, and let the Patient take one ounce at a time, three times in a day, morning, noon and at night, a little before he go to bed. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another drink to take after the ſtone is broken to avoid it in ſlivers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Roſemary and wilde thyme, of each a handfull, and ſeethe them in a quart of rain water, untill the one half be conſumed, and then put in as much Sugar as will make it ſweet,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119654:33"/> and let the Patient drink often thereof every day untill he ſee his water being thick grow thin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Medicine to ſtaunch Bleeding at the Noſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke a linnen cloth and wet it well in Vineger and wrap it about the members of him that bleedeth, and his bleeding will ſoon ceaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Centory, green Rue, and red Fennel, of each a like quantity and ſtamp them all together, and ſtrain them into ale, and let the Patient drink thereof lukewarm, and this will ſtop the bleeding of any wound, cut or bruiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Medicine againſt ſpitting of Blood</head>
                  <p>TAke the juice of Betony, and temper it well with Goats milk and give it the Patient to drink three daies together. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Betony, Mints, Smallidge and Rue, of each a like quantity and ſeeth them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in new milk, and let the Patient drink it as hot as he can ſuffer it. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119654:33"/>
                  <head>A ſingular good Oyl for all manner of Bruiſes, Spleens, Swellings in the legs or arms.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pint or ſomewhat more of pure Sallet Oyl, and bruiſe a good quantity of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momill and put therein, and put it into a glaſs, and ſet it into ſome place where the Sun cometh that it may ſtand ſafe for ten or twelve daies, but when it hath ſtood five daies then take it and ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth, and ſet it again into his place aforeſaid, the remainder of the time aforeſaid, and then ſtrain it again and ſet it the third time, and let it ſtand till it be clean purified from any drugs, and then put it into a clean glaſs and ſtop it cloſe untill you have uſe for it, and then anoint the place grieved two or three times a day chafing it before the fire and it will help you. This Oyl ſtopped cloſe will continue good twelve years.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Medicine for a Bruiſe or Cut.</head>
                  <p>TAke roots of Loveage, Alchoof, Parſly and Anniſeeds, and beat them very fine in a mortar, then take Barrows greaſe and boyl them together, and then ſtrain them, and put to them as much unwrought wax as contains a Walnut, and half as much roſin, and then boyl them all
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119654:34"/> together again, and having ſo done, ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth into a pan of water, and let it ſtand till it be almoſt cold, then take it and work it well in your hands till it be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhort, then put it into a piece of leather and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Drink to heal all manner of Bruiſes.</head>
                  <p>TAke Egremony, Betony, Plantine, Sage, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Jvyleaves, and Parſly, of each a like quantity, and ſtamp them altogether, and mingle them with white-wine, and let the Patient drink thereof and it cureth. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Medicine for a Burning or Scalding, approved.</head>
                  <p>TAke the inner-bark of Elder, the leaves of Alexander, and the leaves of Daſies, boyl them in Hogs-greaſe, then ſtrain them well and anoint the grief with a feather and cover it with a red Colwort-leaf and you will be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſpeedy Remedy for a Woman in Child-birth.</head>
                  <p>TAke a Date-ſtone and grate it to powder, and give a woman in travell to drink in white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine, and ſhe will have a ſpeedy deliverance.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119654:34"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Polipodium or Oke-fearn and ſtamp it very well and make thereof a Plaiſter and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to her feet that is in travell, and it will cauſe a ſpeedy deliverance of the child dead or alive. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Medicine for to help the Kidneys and to cauſe the reins of the Back to grow ſtrong.</head>
                  <p>TAke Buglas water that is diſtilled, and put thereto a good quantity of clean Roſe-water, and a good piece of fine Sugar, and drink there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of every morning faſting, this will reſtore nature and ſtrengthen. Very much approved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent good Salve for any new cut or wound that will not ceaſe Bleeding.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of the blades of Leeks and ſtamp them very well, and put thereto a good quantity of Wheat-flower, and a good quantity of honey and mix them well together, but let it not come near the fire, and lay it cold upon the cut or wound, this will ſtaunch the blood immediatly, and will alſo draw forth all the bruiſed blood, and make clean the wound. <hi>Pro. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:119654:35"/>
                  <head>A very good way to make a ſalve called the Black ſalve, which cureth all old ſores and ulcers, be they never ſo foul.</head>
                  <p>TAke a gallon of ſtale Ale which is ſtrong, two handfuls of Woodbine leaves, half a handfull of ſeeded Nettles, as many Colworts which have ragged leaves upon them, red Onions and Garlick pilled, of each half a pound, one pound of unſet Leeks, one handfull of the powder of a rotten poſt which is of Oak, and ſtamp all theſe well together in a mortar, and put them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into the Ale, with half a pound of Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allum, and then ſet them over a ſoft fire to boyl till the one half be conſumed or more, then ſtrain the ſame through a fine linnen cloth into an earthen pot that is clean, then take one pound of Virgins wax, half a pound of Roſin, half a pound of nerve oyl that is good and green, and a good quantity of ſtone honey, and put them and mingle them with the reſt, then let it ſtand four or five daies, then take it and boyl it again till it be half conſumed, then take it off the fire and put it up into a clean pot, and ſtop it cloſe for your uſe. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119654:35"/>
                  <head>A perfect way to ſet a bone or to heal a broken bone in man or beaſt.</head>
                  <p>TAke the juice of Comfry roots, and wilde Daiſes, boyl them with Turpentine and yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wax, and make a flat Plaiſter therewith, and lay it to the grief and ſet ſplinters about it, and rowl it to keep it ſtiff once in five daies untill it be whole alſo, let the Patient drink the juice of the roots nine daies with the uſe of the Plaiſter. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A proved Medicine againſt the grief of the lungs, and ſpitting of Blood.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the herb Tuſſilago, called at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngula Caballina,</hi> in plain En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Coltsfoot, incorporate it well with the Lard of a Hog chopped with a new laid egge, boyl all together in a pan, and give this to the Patient nine mornings to eat, this will alſo make one fat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Againſt a ſtinking Breath.</head>
                  <p>TAke Roſemary leaves with the bloſſoms, if you can get them, and ſeeth them in white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine, with a little myrrh and Sinamon, and uſe it often in your mouth and you ſhall finde a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119654:36"/> marvellous good effect. And Commin powdred and boyl'd in white wine half the quantity boyld away, and take half a pint at a time mornings and evenings. This will cure in fifteen daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A proved Medicine for an ach or ſore Breaſt.</head>
                  <p>TAke Frankincenſe, fine wrought wax, Boars greaſe and Roſin, of each of them a like quantity, and ſeeth them together to a cake, and ſpread it on a cloth as broad as the ſore or pain, and let it lie twenty four hours, or twenty, or twelve at leaſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a handfull of Mallows, ſeeth them very ſoft in fair water, and then ſtrain them from the water and ſhred them ſmal, then put them in a diſh with Boars-greaſe, and mingle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and heat them very hot, and lay it on a linnen cloth and apply it plaiſter-wiſe to the breaſt hot as you can three or four times a day, and this will help you, as hath been proved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Remedy againſt the Biting of a mad dog, and the raging of madneſs which will follow the party bitten.</head>
                  <p>TAke the bloſſoms of flowers of wilde thiſtle dried in the ſhade and beaten into powder,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119654:36"/> and take the quantity of half a nutſhell full in a ſmal quantity of white-wine and drink it, and in thrice taking of it you will be whole. Approved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Remedy for one that ſpits blood by the breach of a Vein in the Breaſt.</head>
                  <p>TAke Mice-dung beaten into powder, as much as will lie upon a groat, and put it into half a glaſsfull of the juice of Plantine with a little Sugar, and give the Patient thereof to drink morning and evening, continuing it with Gods help he ſhall in a ſhort ſpace be ſound. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Oyntment for a Bruiſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pound of <hi>May</hi> butter without ſalt, and ſet it on the fire, and when it is boyled ſcum off the froth, and then put into it one handfull of Roſemary, Bayleaves, Fennell, Wormwood, Smallidge, of each a handfull, ſhred them ſmal and boyl them in the butter till it look green, then put into it Bees-wax, Roſin, Frankincenſe, of each one pennyworth, and let them melt but not boyl in it, when they are melted ſtrain them, it is good for a Sprain or Bruiſe or any old Ach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119654:37"/>
                  <head>An approved Medicine to ſtaunch Blood at the noſe, or any Vein that is cut.</head>
                  <p>TAke feathers and burn to powder and lay upon the Vein that is cut, and take a wet cloth and lap it round about the members, and lay it on cold three times and it will ſtaunch blood wherever.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Compoſition of a moſt excellent and pretious Oyntment to heal preſently any Scalding or Burning with fire, hot water or powder, or whatſoever elſe, being preſently applied, at which time it will work the beſt effect and hinder all bliſtering and breakings out, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of it cannot be parellelled.</head>
                  <p>TAke a wine pint of Oyl-olive and put into a clean pipkin, then gather ſome of the Elder tree ſprigs no bigger then the top of your finger, and a handfull of the ſmalleſt and young leaves, ſcrape off lightly the upper rinde of the ſprigs and caſt it away, then ſcrape off the ſecond rinde which is green and reſerve about a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of that which together with the leaves put into a pipkin with the oyl, take alſo a few Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119654:37"/> leaves and leaves of Sengreen and put them in alſo, and adde alſo a ſixth part of ſtrong white-wine Vineger, two or three ſpoonfuls of Urine, about two inches of a cotton candle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the wick, let all theſe boyl together at a ſoft fire, ſtirring it now and then, then ſtrain it through a courſe linnen cloth, and put that which you ſtrain out into the pipkin again, and put to it a little yellow wax and let it melt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtill ſtirring it till it come to an ointment or ſalve, which you may keep in a Vial or box, when you will uſe it ſpread it thin upon a paper or linnen cloth and lay it to the place burned, and let it lie twenty four hours, if you do apply it in this ſort preſently upon the ſcald or burning it will take out the fire and hinder bliſtering and redneſs, and healeth it in half a quarter of an hour, it is alſo ſoveraign againſt the ſwelling or inflammation of the legs, and alſo for any heat whatſoever. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> Matthias, <hi>or the Lukatella Oyl or Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, called Cordius Balſom.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe vertues of it are many, as followeth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> It is very effectual againſt the watering of the Lungs, taking the quantity of a hazel nut in the morning faſting.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo good to heal a wound inward or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119654:38"/> being ſearing inwardly, and applied to the outward with fine linnen cloth or lint, as hot as may be indured.</p>
                  <p>It doth draw forth broken bones or any thing which may putrifie or feſter if the brain be not touched.</p>
                  <p>It is good againſt burnings, ſcaldings, bruiſes or cuts.</p>
                  <p>It taketh away pains or griefs that proceed of moiſture, as Aches in the bones or ſinews, firſt anointing the part grieved and then applying a warm cloth.</p>
                  <p>It alſo helpeth the headach anointing the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or noſthrils therewith, and taking a little quantity inward.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo good againſt the winde chollick or a ſtitch in the ſide, applying thereto warm with hot clothes a quarter of an hour.</p>
                  <p>It expelleth poyſon and helpeth a ſurfeit by taking one ounce at once four mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>It helpeth the biting of a mad dog, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mad beaſt, the quantity of one ounce taken in a little warm Sack.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo good againſt the Plague, anointing the lips and noſthrils in the morning.</p>
                  <p>It is alſo good for a Fiſtula or Ulcer.</p>
                  <p>It is good for one infected with the Plague or ſmal Pox or Meaſels preſently taken in hot broth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119654:38"/> a quarter of an ounce four mornings together, ſweating after it.</p>
                  <p>It is good alſo for worms or a canker.</p>
                  <p>It doth help digeſtion. anointing the ſtomack and navil therewith going to bed.</p>
                  <p>It ſtauncheth the bleeding of freſh wounds laying a Plaiſter of lint upon the wound, and tying it hard on.</p>
                  <p>This Balſom will do no good if any thing be applied before or between it to the wound or grief, you may keep it twenty years, the longer the better. <hi>Prob. eſt</hi> for all theſe things.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>The way to make this Balſom.</head>
                  <p>Take a pint and half of Sallet-oyl and beat it with one pint of Sack, <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine one pound, beat it in Damask-roſe water, ſtill pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it out till the Turpentine look white, yellow wax four ounces, melt it in a great earthen pot or pipkin and adde to it the former ingredients, ſtirring them altogether till they boyl, then take it from the fire, put in one ounce of red Sanders, then let it boyl one hour, then take it off and keep it in a gallypot for your uſe, which you may do by Plaiſter as well as by fommatation and tents. <hi>Prob. eſt</hi> for the griefs aforeſaid.</p>
                  <p>The way to prepare your Sanders is thus,</p>
                  <p>Take your quantity of Sanders and make
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119654:39"/> paſte thereof with the ſharpeſt wine Vinegar you can get, and roul it round, and bake it with white bread and let it after ſtand a while to dry, and when it is thorow dry pound it well and ſearce it for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another direction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take your Sack, ſet it on the fire, put into it the wax and let them boyl together till the wax is well melted, then put into it half your Oyl, but let it not boyl after the Oyl is in, then take it off and let it cool, and when it is cold, put from it the Sack, and pour in the reſt of your ingredients letting them well melt but not boyl, then take it off again and as it is cooling put in your red Sanders and put it up into a new veſſel which was never uſed; if you have any of the <hi>naturea</hi> Balſom put ſome of it therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A ſpecial good black Plaiſter or ſear-cloth to lay to any wound, or to eaſe any ach or ſwelling, or to draw out any thorns: approved by the Lady</hi> Grimſtone.</head>
                  <p>TAke Sallet oyl and Neatsfoot oyl, of each half a pint, and put therein half a pound of red lead beaten very ſmal, and as you ſtrew it in a little at once ſtirre it well, then ſet it on the coals of a ſoft fire, and let it boyl till it look
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119654:39"/> black, then put in as much roſin as contains the bigneſs of an egge beaten ſmal, ſtirre it well all the time it is boyling, let it not boyl too faſt leaſt it boyl over, drop a little upon a pewter diſh, and if it rowl off without hanging then it is enough, and ſo may you make plaiſters or dip in clothes without fremes for ſear-clothes, take Sallet-oyl in want of Neats-foot. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for a combuſtion or Burning with Gun-powder.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke out the fire firſt by linſeed-oyl and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beaten together, more water then oyl, Plantine water is beſt, you may for your uſe dip in lane or fine <hi>Holland</hi> clothes. Then take of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum album</hi> half an ounce, and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum poppillion</hi> and warm them in a porringer, and with a feather anoint the combuſtion, then lay on dry clothes upon the combuſtion.</p>
                  <p>And then if any ſpungy fleſh ariſe,</p>
                  <p>Take ſpirit <hi>revinum</hi> one ounce, and put in ſeven drops of <hi>oleum vitriolum</hi> and with a probe armed with lint dip it in the medicine and waſh the Ulcer therewith ſpreading a cloth with <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum album</hi> and lay over it, and ſo do till your cure be done.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119654:40"/>
                  <head>A ſpecial Remedy for a weak Back.</head>
                  <p>TAke a new laid egge and put out al the yeolk, and then take as much white amber as will lie on a groat heapt, and put it into your egge with Muskedine, and drink it in the morning as ſoon as you can and lie one hour or two after it, and if you can ſleep, and at the two hours or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, and after you have taken it take a draught of candle made with whites of egges and no yeolks.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Direction how to make a wholſom meſs of Broth for a ſick body, whoſe ſtomack is not good.</head>
                  <p>TAke the yeolks of two egges, put them in a little pipkin for that purpoſe, ſqueeſe therein the juice of a lemon or two, then take a good ladlefull of ſome broth out of another pot that boyls, firſt beat the egges and lemon well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and put in the ſaid broth, make it not ſalt by no means, then ſtirre altogether upon a ſoft fire, at the firſt boyl take it off, and when it is cool enough give it the Patient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To ſtaunch Blood.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Sanguis Draconis,</hi> bole armonick, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>million, of each a like quantity, compound
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119654:40"/> them with the white of egges beat it to the form of a plaiſter, this hath ſtaied the blood of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans breaſt that was cut off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To purge the Back and Brain.</head>
                  <p>TAke the powder of Bettony and Engliſh honey and make a doſe of pils and take two pils thereof when you go to bed, as big as a ſmal nut, next morning you ſhall ſee the effect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a pain in the Back.</head>
                  <p>TAke a plaiſter of Paracelſus and lay thereon warm, and it cureth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To ſcale a mortified Bone.</head>
                  <p>TAke honey of Roſes, and dip ſpledgets of lint therein, and lay it on the bone till you finde the bone looſe, dreſs it every night for three nights, if it do not then looſen by the ſides in feeling, then apply this unguent or ointment,</p>
                  <p>Take pure hogs-greaſe half a pound, <hi>argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vivum</hi> two ounces well mortified and bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, warm the Unguent in a ſawcer or porringer, and with a feather anoint the bone morning and evening and lay thereon lint, and rowl it up juſt let him keep his bed and take no
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119654:41"/> cold and you ſhall ſee the bone ariſe, then heal it up as you ſee occaſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>The Black plaiſter that mundifieth all ſores and taketh away all pain.</head>
                  <p>TAke Sallet-oyl and white-wine Vineger twelve ounces, white lead and red lead of each two ounces, wax three ounces, boyl them altogether till they be black, and when you have taken it from the fire adde two drams of cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire prepared and mix it well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A powder which ſcaleth Bones and ſtoppeth the watering of ſinews.</head>
                  <p>TAke burned Copras one ounce, <hi>auri pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum</hi> fine combuſt one ounce, Verdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe ſinely ſearced one ounce, burned Allum fine powdered and ſearced three ounces, mix them together, ſo uſe them, it is excellent in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame and to abate ſpungy fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke fine Allum, Verdigreaſe, of each two ounces, Bole four ounces finely powdered, mix altogether, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119654:41"/>
                  <head>A good Medicine to cure any Diſeaſe which proceeds from the Breaſt.</head>
                  <p>TAke Parſly roots, Fennell roots, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cory roots of each a like quantity, take out the piths clean and waſh away the dirt and ſand from them, and then ſeeth them in white-wine till they be ſoft, and then when it is well boyled ſtrain them and adde thereto a little Pellitory of <hi>Spain,</hi> and let the Patient drink hereof morning and evening for the ſpace of eight or nine daies together, this hath holpen thoſe which could not fetch their breath at all hardly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Remedy for a Chin chough.</head>
                  <p>TAke Bores-greaſe and warm the feet of the Patient againſt the fire, and chafe and rub in the ſaid greaſe well, and then let the Patient go to bed and be kept very warm, ſpecially his feet. This may be done to little Children. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a Mouſe and flay it, and dry it in an oven, and beat it to powder, and give it the Patient to drink in a quantity of Ale and it will help him, and it is alſo good for thoſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119654:42"/> that cannot hold their water. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, and for the ſtraitneſs of the Pipes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke dry Figges and Hyſope and ſtamp them well together, and boyl them well with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and let the Patient take it faſting and it will help. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, a Syrup.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Horehound and Hyſope of each a like quantity, and a little water and ſugar and boyl theſe together till they come to be a Syrup, let the Patient eat this morning and evening and at other convenient times. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, a pure one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Ellecampany and Reddiſh roots a like quantity and ſhred them ſmall, and pears or wardens twice the quantity as of the other, then put them together into an earthen pot, and put as much clarified Honey thereto as will make it ready to overflow the ſaid ingredients, then cover it cloſe that no breath iſſue out, then ſet it in an oven &amp; bake it with a batch of bread, and then when it is baked give of this morning
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119654:42"/> and evening a ſpoonfull and at noon to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A perfect Syrup for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke half a pound of white Sugar-candy, and half a pint of Roſewater, and a good quantity of Licoriſh clean pared and bruiſed, boyl all theſe together untill you ſee it come to a Syrup, then ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth and put it in a glaſs and keep it for your uſe. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Medicine to take away Corns.</head>
                  <p>TAke black Sope and Snails, of each of them a like quantity, and ſtamp them together, and make a plaiſter thereof and ſpread it upon a piece of white leather and lay it to the Corn, and it will take it away within ſeven or eight daies. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Medicine to avoid Choller.</head>
                  <p>TAke half an ounce of Caſſia which is new drawn, and a dram of Rubarb, and let them be infuſed for the ſpace of a night with water of indive and a little Spiknard, and one ounce of Syrup of Violets and mingle them together with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119654:43"/> the quantity of three or four ounces of whey, and let the Patient drink it warm. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A proved Medicine for the Strangury, Chollick and Stone.</head>
                  <p>TAke Gromell ſeed, Parſly and red Nettle ſeed, Violet leaves, Smalledge, Cherry ſtones, Philopendula, Eli ſanders, Saxifrage, Cummin ſeed and Fennell ſeed. Anniſeed and Coriander ſeed, Sowthiſtle and Dill ſeed, of each of them a like quantity, beat them very ſmall in a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and ſearce them fine, then take the Gum of Ivy or elſe the Berries of Ivy dried and beaten to powder, and mingle with the powder afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and let the Patient drink this powder in white-wine or ſtale Ale or in his pottage morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening for eight or nine daies. <hi>Prob. est.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Clyſter for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke Mallows, Pellitory of the wall and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus Benedictus,</hi> Colworts, Setrach, and Oak-fearn, and Alkabergi ſeeds, of each a like quantity, and make thereof a Decoction, then adde oyl of Dill and Camomili, and oyl of Lillies, of each one dram, and of <hi>Hiera ſimplex</hi> and ſalt, and ſo apply it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119654:43"/>
                  <head>An approved Medicine againſt the grief of the Flank and the Chollick paſſion.</head>
                  <p>TAke half a glaſs or leſs of the juice of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries when they be very ripe and red, and put into it as much red Corall in powder as will lie upon a groat, and give the Patient to drink.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another perfect one for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke fine powder of <hi>Virga aurea,</hi> and put one ſpoonfull of it into a new laid egge ſoft roſted, and give it the Patient in a morning fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and let him faſt four hours after it, and he will ſuddenly make water, uſe this for ten or twelve daies, and the Patient will void the Stone without any pain. <hi>Prob. est.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To cure a Cough that comes by cold ſuddenly.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>aqua vitae</hi> and Sallet-oyl, and loaf Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, mingle them together when you go to bed, take a quantity of it, and in the morning when you ariſe alſo it will take away your cough and eaſe your lungs. Proved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To cure the Wind chollick.</head>
                  <p>TAke Sea-horſe pisfle, Harts horn and <hi>enula campana</hi> of each one dram finely powdered,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119654:44"/> take as much of this in a morning faſting as will lie on a groat or ſomewhat more in a cup of Anniſeed water. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Conſumption a noted Cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quarter of a pound of <hi>Jordan</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds blanched and beat ſmall, adding thereto in the beating ſome Roſewater one or two ſpoonfuls, then take the thigh of a roſted Capon flay off the skin beat it in a mortar alone, then take fourteen Dates ſtoned, skinned and picked and beat them alone, then put them all in a pint of Roſewater with ſome Sugar and boyl them three walms, then take Sinamon two drams, Lignum and Aloes both powdered one dram, put them in your Decoction and ſtirre them well together, and put it up into ſome Viall, and take the quantity of a Walnut at once in the morning faſting, the firſt three mornings adde to it every time two grains of Bezor.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Diet-drink for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt week in <hi>May</hi> infuſe in your uſual drink Succory, Devils bit, Scabions, water creſſes. Lungwort, Polipodium, Coltsfoot, Pennyroyal, Liverwort of each two handfuls bruiſed and put in a fine linnen cloth bag, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119654:44"/> ſo put it in your drink when it is new tunned, to work therein and this you will finde very good, drink no other drink for fourteen daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make an Inciſion to take out a corrupt Coar.</head>
                  <p>TAke Roſe alger and powder it fine and mix it with Hogs-greaſe, and lay it on ſo broad as you will have the Coar come out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A perfect cure for a Canker.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pint of white-wine Vinegar, and take Strawbery leaves, Colibine leaves, red Sage leaves, Woodbine, Violet and red briar leaves of each a handfull and ſet your Vinegar upon a ſoft fire, and put in your herbs, and let them boyl till they be ſoft, then ſtrain your leaves hard out and keep it in a Viall for your uſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke running water a pint, Woodbine, Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Colibine leaves, of each a handfull, and a little Roſemary, boyl all theſe together till half the water be waſted, then ſtrain it, and adde thereto two or three ſpoonfuls of Honey, and a little of Roach-allum three or four ſpoonfuls of white-wine Vinegar, and ſo waſh the mouth with the herbs three or four times a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119654:45"/>
                  <head>Chollick the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Gum hederue warm it that it may ſpread and ſpread it upon a piece of Scarlet as big as a ſhilling or broader, and apply it to the navil. Your beſt Gum is ſweet, clear and ſoft. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Conſumption. Proved.</head>
                  <p>TAke Diaſcordium, Flower of brimſtone, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve of red Roſes, and make this into little bals and lay one of them under your tongue when you go to bed, and let it diſſolve in your mouth, alſo take Coltsfoot and white amber and Anniſeeds altogether in a pipe mornings and evenings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Remedy for the biting of a mad Dog.</head>
                  <p>TAke Nightſhed, Bettony and wilde Sage, each of them a handfull, and one pint of fair running water, and ſtamp the herbs and ſtrain them with the water, and then put thereto a pennyworth of good Treakle and give it the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to drink three or four mornings together faſting, and this will help him ſpeedily. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119654:45"/>
                  <head>An excellent Diet-drink for any diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke a new earthen pot and fill it full of fair running water, only wanting about a quart of being full, and then adde thereto about a quart of white-wine, and ſet the pot over a ſoft fire of coales, and put into the pot a pound of good Licoriſh ſcraped clean and ſliced, and half a pound of Anniſeeds bruiſed, half a pound of <hi>Lignum vitae</hi> which you may have at the Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and one ounce of the bark which is of the ſame tree, which you may have at the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, adde thereto a ſmall quantity of China and Saxifrage, and a little Centory, let all theſe boyl on the fire about two hours, or untill you ſee a good part of the liquor conſumed, then ſtrain it into another clean earthen veſſell and ſtop it cloſe, and drink a good draught thereof morning and evening and at noon a while after dinner. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119654:46"/>
                  <head>A moſt excellent Wine made of Sage for to be drunk at all times, if you waſh your mouth therewith it will help the Tooth-ach and pains of the gums, it is good for the Palſie, and for the Cramp, and for Lunatick perſons, it reſtoreth ſinews ſhrunk, it expelleth ill humors out of the body, it is alſo good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Plague and Piſtilence.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Sage, both white and red and boyl it very well in Muskedine and then ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth and with a tunnell put it into a glaſs and ſtop it cloſe, and when the Patient will uſe it let him drink a good draught thereof morning and evening for a certain ſpace, and according to the grief where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is troubled, and this will perfectly heal all the diſeaſes aforeſaid. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent Medicine for the Dropſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke roots of kneeholm and Parſly roots and Fennell roots, of each of them finely ſcraped and ſliced a good handfull, of Juniper Berries half a handfull, and of Anniſeed and Alexander ſeed each of them a ſpoonfull, boyl all theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in three pints of clear poſſet-ale, boyling
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119654:46"/> to a quart, then take a handfull of dead Bees and ſtamp them in a wooden diſh and ſtrain them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this poſſet-ale, and ſo let the Patient drink every five hours a good draught thereof and this will help him in a ſhort ſpace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Medicine for a deaf and pained Ear.</head>
                  <p>TAke earth-worms and fry them with Gooſe-greaſe and drop a little thereof warm into the ear grieved, this uſed nine or ten times will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, and hath cured ſome which could not hear almoſt at all, and were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled therewith twenty years.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a Hedgehog and flay him and roſt him, and let the Patient put ſome of the greaſe or fat that comes from him into his ear, and he will recover his hearing in a ſhort ſpace. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A comfortable powder to cauſe one to Digeſt his meat.</head>
                  <p>TAke Pellitory of <hi>Spain,</hi> Centory, Anniſeeds, Licoriſh grains of Paradiſe, Ginger, Cino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, of each of them a like quantity, and beat them and ſearce them into fine powder, and let
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119654:47"/> the Patient drink half a ſpoonfull at a time there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in white-wine, ale or beer, morning and evening for a certain ſpace, and this will do much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Treakle to cure the Dropſie or any other Diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke the powder of Rue and Bettony, of each ten ounces, Centory and Wormwood of each three drams, Gentian myrrh, <hi>Oriſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia rotunda</hi> and Ivory, of each one ounce, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verize and ſearce all theſe and mix them with honey clarified to a Treakle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Drink to be made in</hi> May, <hi>good for many Diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke Scabious Mugwort, Smallidge, Devils bit, ground Ivy, Wormwood, Fumitory, Fetherfew, Spicknard, of each two handfuls, boyl them well in whey made in <hi>May,</hi> and when they be well boyled put in the laſt walm the whites of ſix egges and ſome clarified Honey, a little Saffron, the powder of about a dozen Cloves, then ſtrain it and drink it faſting for ſome time in that moneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:119654:47"/>
                  <head>A drink for the Dropſie called roots drink.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Wormwood and of the tops of green broom, Sear Bean ſhels, of each two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, dry them in an oven, and beat them to powder, then put the powder into a quart of white-wine, let it ſtand twenty four hours, then ſtrain it through a piece of white new cotton four or five times, then let the Patient drink four or five ſpoonfuls in a morning, and as many at noon, and as many at night. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Purge for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke Mechoachan Sugar Diagredii, Rubarb, Sena, Spiknard, of each a dram, Anniſeed two ſcruples, Cinomon, Maſtick, Ginger, of each one ſcruple, let all theſe be fine powdered, the doſe or quantity to take at one time in white-wine or poſſet-ale three daies together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Powder for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke Dragons, Spiknard, of each one ounce, and Alchenet half an ounce, powder them and drink as much as will lie on a ſix pence in ale or beer, faſting and at night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119654:48"/>
                  <head>A Diet for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke Juniper thin ſhaved, and the Berries bruiſed, Aſh-bark, Saſafras roots, Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort roots, Caper roots, Camock roots, Marſh-mallow roots of each a handfull, Parſly roots, Eringo roots, Fennell roots, all bruiſed, of each two ounces, Parſly and Fennell ſeeds bruiſed, of each one ounce, put all this in a pipkin cloſe covered, put upon them as much skalding wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as will cover them, then ſtop it cloſe with paſte, and let it ſtand in hot embers and not boyl for twenty four hours, then put all into a firkin of new Ale of ſeven gallons, and let it work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till the Ale be ſtale and drink this at all times and no other drink till you, with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, be well. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another excellent Potion for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Rue, Sage, Bettony, Polipodium of the Oak, Water-creſſes, green Broom, Hyſſop, Parſly and Fennell roots, Lovadge roots, and Flower deluce, Gladwine the middle, and of the Elder the ſmall clot burre, of each of theſe a handfull, your roots muſt be pithed or the pithes taken out, boyl theſe in Barly-water and white-wine of each a like quantity, mix it with pure
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119654:48"/> Honey <hi>quod ſufficit,</hi> or as you ſhall ſee meet, of this let the Patient drink firſt and laſt. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Dropſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke a penny-wait of Scammony, two penny-wait of Rubarb, ſix penny-wait of Senny, one dram of Setwell, one penny-wait of Spiknard, Cammomill-flowers one dram, beat all theſe to powder and ſearce them, and adde thereto one ounce of Sugar, and take thereof every morning one ſpoonfull. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An Oyntment for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of Cream, one pint of Hodman dods, one handfull of Houſleek, one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Brook-lime, boyl all theſe together and anoint the grief and it will take down the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Dropſie the Cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Tare half a pound, Sallet-oyl two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Bay-ſalt beat to powder one ſpoonfull, ſet them upon a ſoft fire and let them ſimper a while, then take it off and keep it for your uſe, anoint and bathe the grieved joynts therewith, and binde it hard with a linnen cloth. Approved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119654:49"/>
                  <head>A good powder to cauſe Digeſtion.</head>
                  <p>TAke Pellitory of <hi>Spain,</hi> Centory, Anniſeeds, Licoriſh, grains of Paradiſe, Ginger and Cinamon, of each a like quantity, beat them to fine powder, and let the Patient drink a ſpoonful hereof in Ale, Wine or Beer, morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a good ſpace. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Medicine to deſtroy an Impoſthume in twenty four hours or little more.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the Flower-deluce, and Lilly roots, of each of them a good quantity and ſtamp them together and put them into a quart of Honey, and boyl them altogether in wine or ſtrong ale, and when they are well ſodden, then take the ſame liquor and ſtrain through a fine linnen cloth, and when you will uſe it let the Patient drink two or three ſpoonfuls of it morning and evening and at noon, ſometime let the Patient drink Plantine and Wormwood mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther firſt and laſt. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of the juice of Mints and put it into a quill, and let it run into the Patients ear where the grief is, and let it lie with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119654:49"/> that ear upward and that will cauſe the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthume to break ſpeedily.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious water for ſore Eyes which do run or look red. Approved by my ſelf many times.</head>
                  <p>TAke white Vitrioll or Copras a piece about the bigneſs of a good haſell nut and beat it to fine powder then take a pint of pure ſpring wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and put it into a Viall, then take a new laid egge and break it, put only the white into a diſh, uſe the yeolk for what you pleaſe, beat the white very well, then put that with the Vitreol into your Vial of water, and in two hours you may uſe it. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke the Celeſtiall ſtone or blew Vitrioll and ſteep the ſtone in fair ſpring water till the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be coloured, then take out the ſtone and waſh your eyes therewith, this is alſo good to waſh any ſore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another to allay the heat of the Eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke womans milk white Roſewater and eye-bright water, and Plantine water, of each a like quantity, and diſſolve in them one grain
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119654:50"/> of Camphire, drop this water into the eyes and lay li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>le linnen clothes dipped in it, and lay to the eyes all night. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pure water for a pin and a web, or any film in the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>TAke roots and leaves of Daiſies, and Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoof, and Solendine and ground Ivy, of each a like quantity, and ſtamp and ſtrain them and ſave the juice and put into the juice a little piece of pure white Sugar, and let it diſſolve therein, and drop in ſome of it into the eye grieved, and in four or five times dreſſing it will take away the film.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A water for ſore Eyes, let it come either by inward or outward cauſes.</head>
                  <p>TAke two ſpoonfuls of the juice of Fennell, and one ſpoonfull and an half of the juice of Solendine, Honey twice as much as both, boyl them a little upon a chafendiſh of coals, ſcum away the dregs that you ſee ariſe, and when it is half cold ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth, and put it into a Viall glaſs and ſtop it cloſe and anoint the eyes with this when occaſion ſerves and it will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:119654:50"/>
                  <head>A rare ſecret for a pearl or web in the Eye.</head>
                  <p>TAke nine worms which you ſhall finde in an old hollow tree or timber, with many legs, called Hogs-lice, ſtamp them with the juice of Solendine or Bettony, then ſtrain it and drink it warm faſting, eat not in two hours after it, uſe this three mornings together. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For ſore Eyes.</head>
                  <p>TAke Wood bettony and beat it to powder, and take as much as will lie on a ſix pence each morning till they be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An admirable and perfect cure for the Falling Sickneſs, which I have proved often with good ſucceſs.</head>
                  <p>TAke the dung of a Peacock and dry it in an oven, and make it into fine powder, and into one ounce and a half of it adde half a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce of Amber peretah known by the name of Scuchenelle at the Apothecaries, and adde alſo three leaves of pure gold of leaf-gold, your Amber peretah will eaſily diſſolve, and your way to diſſolve the gold is thus, Do not touch it with your hand, but lay your powder
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119654:51"/> aforeſaid upon the gold, and ſtill with your fore-finger and your thumb be ſtirring it about till your gold doth diſſolve under the powder, mix about half a ſpoonfull of this powder with a little black-berry water when the fit is coming, and it will cure the force thereof, give it the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient for a time firſt and laſt, and it will for ever cure it although it have reigned twenty years, provided firſt you adminiſter this drink fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
                  <p>Take a good handfull of Camamill, another of Wood-bettony, half a handfull of Yarrow, a few Marrygold flowers, half a handfull of red Sage leaves, green Elder leaves half a handfull, of Licoriſh one ounce, of Anniſeeds one ounce, Figges half a pound, Raiſins ſtoned half a pound, boyl all theſe together in a pottle of fair running water to a pint, and then put in two ounces of Sugar candy, of the beſt, after it is boyled, and let it ſtand unſtrained twelve hours, then ſtrain it and let the Patient drink thereof firſt and laſt a quarter of a pint at a time about one moneth, and at times ſome of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer powder, and with Gods bleſſing it will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi> This I have kept as a ſecret.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke the brains of a Weezel and dry it to powder put it into ſome pure white-wine Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119654:51"/> and temper them well together with a knife and give it the Patient to drink firſt and laſt, and it will help him. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith that he knew many men in his time cured by drinking the powder of dead mens bones, and in another place he ſaith that the skull of a dead man taken from the earth and waſhed very clean and dried in an oven and beaten to powder will alſo, taken in their drink, cure them, although it have reigned many years, but he ſaith it muſt be the skull of one that hath been ſlain or hanged, and not of one that died by any ſickneſs, becauſe maladies in the head in time of ſickneſs will take away the vertue thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Germander in <hi>May</hi> when it is bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom'd, dry it in the ſhadow and make it into powder, and when you will uſe it take the yeolk of an egge or two and ſtirre and break it with a ſpoonfull of the ſaid powder then ſeeth it and give it the Patient to eat morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eight daies, let the Patient abſtain from wine and carnall company of women and from all pulce, beans or peaſe, or any tares and from ſallets and ſalt fiſh, and from all other things that be hard of concoction and digeſtion. This is a very pretious Receipt.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:119654:52"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke the blood, liver and heart of a Mole, and dry them to powder and let the Patient take one dram in a little pine water faſting, and faſt two hours after it, uſe it ſix mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and it will cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a woman that hath too much of her Flowers.</head>
                  <p>TAke the foot of a Hare, burn it to powder, and drink of it in red wine and Cinamon firſt and laſt nine daies and it will cure her.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good drink to cauſe Fleam to be avoided.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Hyſope water, a quart of good Muskedine, three or four ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of good caſe Ginger pared clean, and cut in ſmall ſlices, and twice as much Licoriſh ſcraped, alſo then put thereto a good handfull of fine Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-candy bruiſed, put them altogether in a big glaſs to ſtand and ſoak well, and ſo let it ſtand for the ſpace of twenty four hours together, but ſhake it often in that time, let the glaſs be well ſtopped, and let the Patient drink this at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, this hath cured ſuch as could hardly ſpeak for Fleam.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:119654:52"/>
                  <head>Pils good to ſtop the bloody Flux.</head>
                  <p>TAke Marmalet of Quinces two ounces, and of Corall, Cinamon, Amber, Shepherds purſe, Alchemet, Acatia, of each two drams, powder them and ſearce them and mix them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into a maſe for Pils, take four of theſe Pils morning and evening. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a quart of milk and ſet it on the fire, and when it ſeethes put in a piece of Roch-allum, then will ariſe a curd, which when you have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, drink the whey as hot as you can, and if your ſtomack will bear it eat the curd alſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious Medicine to cleanſe the breaſt of Fleam.</head>
                  <p>TAke of white-wine and water, of each one pint, wine Vinegar ten ſpoonfuls, Engliſh honey clarified with whites of egges ſix ounces, Fennell, Parſly roots and Licoriſh all mundified and then ſliced, of each one ounce, <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana</hi> powdred two drams, Egrimony one ounce and a half, and twelve figs cut in pieces, Anniſe and Commine ſeed, Hyſope, Thyme and Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royall,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119654:53"/> of each one ounce and a half, boyl all theſe together cloſe covered till the one half be waſted or a third part, and then ſtrain it and drink thereof morning and evening till you be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a Fiſtula, the whole cure.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt purge the humour offending, then take the ſoles of old ſhoes dried, burnt in a clean harth with oaken wood to a bright coal, then lay it where it may conſume to aſhes alone, then adde to the weight of the aſhes of the ſole, and half ſo much weight of the powder of burnt Allum, then grinde all theſe together on a Painters ſtone or in a mortar to fine ſubtill pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo put it cloſe up for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To tent the Fiſtula.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the Cream of morning milk of one Cow, and ſet it by it ſelf all night, the next day caſt away the greeniſh water from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of that Cream, then lay a ſpoonfull of the Cream on a trencher, then mix ſo much of the powders therewith as will make the Cream black and thick, then make your tents of one inch long and no longer, although the Fiſtula be never ſo deep, and roul the tents well in the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119654:53"/> Medicine, and tent your wound therewith twice in a day and it will work out in ſmall puſhes and wheals from the bottom, cover the ſore with a red Colwort leaf, and when it is well digeſted heal it up with plaiſters fir for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A vulnary potion for the Fiſtula.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of ſpring water, and boyl there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Cloves bruiſed, Pimpernell, Egrimony, red Colwort, Valerian, Mouſear, Dovefoot and wilde Tanzy waſhed and chopped, of each one handfull, boyl all in a pipkin cloſe covered, till half be waſted, then adde to it two ſpoonfuls of Honey, and one quart of white-wine, then let it boyl one walm or two and ſtrain it hard forth, and keep it in a cloſe Viall and drink of it morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening and at three in the afternoon, in Summer cold and in Winter hot, untill the Potion cometh out of the orefice of the Fiſtula, which muſt be alway kept open with a Gentian tent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A plaiſter to cure the Fiſtula.</head>
                  <p>TAke Latherage of Gold one pound, oyl of Roſes two pound, white-wine Vinegar and old Urine, of each half a pound, boyl theſe till the Vinegar and Urine be conſumed, adde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in the boyling, Wax two ounces, Frankincenſe one ounce, mix it and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:119654:54"/>
                  <head>A Lotion to waſh or ſeering into the Fiſtula.</head>
                  <p>TAke Bolearmoniack four ounces, Camphire one ounce white Vitrioll four ounces, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all theſe boil the Copras and Camphire in a cloſe ſtopped pipkin till they be melted, ſtill ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them till they grow hard, then powder them and the Bolearmoniack together very fine, and when you uſe it take a pottle of running water, put it to the fire till it begin to boyl, then take it from the fire and put therein three ſpoonfuls of the powder, as much as the ſpoon will hold, put all into a double Viall and ſhake it twice every day for fourteen daies before you uſe it let it ſtand and ſettle very clear, and apply it as hot as the Patient can endure it, if it be for a ſore wet a double cloth four times double and apply it, if for a Fiſtula uſe the ſearing morning and evening till you be well, if you would have it ſtronger put into it one ounce of burned allum powdered. This is approved either for Fiſtula or Puſtels, Cankers, Scabs in the head or body, and alſo green wounds.</p>
                  <p>Unto your Lotion for Fiſtula you may adde Strawberries, Plantine, red mader, ſharp dock, of each one handfull, let your Cloves be twelve in number, and if you will ſix ounces of honey, if the Patient vomit up his Lotion three daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119654:54"/> at the firſt taking, there is fear of his cure; but if he vomit not, no fear of the cure; let him drink it fourteen daies, in his drinking thereof put in ſome Ginger to allay the winde of the hearbs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An Implaiſter of Tapſus Barbatus which cureth all Cankers, Fiſtulas, Plague-ſores, hot Bruiſes, Botches, or Fellones.</head>
                  <p>TAke the juice of Smallidge and Cardus, young Wormwood, Mullin, Walwort, Pimpernell, Dovefoot, Plantine, Egrimony, Mugwort, Sage, Daiſes, Night-ſhade and Flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellin, of each one dram, Woodbine four hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, ſtamp them and ſtrain them, put to as much Honey in meaſure as you have in juices, then boyl them together in a new red pipkin cloſe covered, let them boyl ſoftly ſtill ſtirring it till it come to the thickneſs of Honey, then take it from the fire and keep it in a new earthen pot cloſe covered. And when you make a Plaiſter for any the things aforeſaid,</p>
                  <p>Take of this Honey four ounces, wheat-meal two ounces, boyl altogether one walm or two ſtill ſtirring it for fear of burning, then take it from the fire and put to it preſently <hi>Venice</hi> Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine two ounces, mix it well with the reſt, and when it is almoſt cold pour the whites of two
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119654:55"/> egges well beaten thereto, mix them together till it be cold, and ſo it is made. The Plaiſter is called <hi>Diafloſmos.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Lotion to waſh or ſeringe the grief withall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you apply the Plaiſter, dreſs it twice a day either by bathe or ſearing hot.</head>
                  <p>TAke Night-ſhade, Smallidge, Egrimony, Fluelline, Sage, Cardus, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Honey two ounces, Plantine water and white-wine, of each one pint, boyl all theſe hearbs ſmall cut till their ſubſtance be forth with the Honey, Allum, Wine and water, and ſo ſtrain it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A perfect Remedy for the Flux.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good handfull of Beans, dry them in an oven or upon a tileſtone, and let them be ſo hard as the huls will skale off them, and then bray them to fine powder and ſearce them, then take a plot of good red wine and ſet it upon the fire, and put the powder into the wine, and ſtirre it well leaſt it ſhould grow to the pan wherein you boyl it, and ſo do till it be ſo thick that you may cut it in ſlices when it is cold, and let the Patient take two or three ſlices there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of blood warm every morning and evening for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119654:55"/> a certain ſpace, and this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Falling ſickneſs, the cure.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt every full Moon and change, purge one day and vomit another, then kill a Jay and dreſs him, fill his body full of Commin and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds bruiſed, then put the Jay ſo dreſſed into an oven after bread is drawn forth, untill he be ſo dry that you muſt beat his body and ſides, and all into fine powder, then take of this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one dram in any thing what you pleaſe morning and evening till you be well, as in broth or ſuch like only, with it make two plaiſters, as you do of Maſtick, of <hi>Sanguis Draconis,</hi> ſpread it with a hot knife, and lay them to the temple veins.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Fiſtula, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Vervine and dry it upon a tile and make powder thereof, and make clean the ſore with a linnen cloth, and fill the wound full with the powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Gout.</head>
                  <p>TAke Arſmart and wet it in fair running wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and lay it to the place grieved, and when you take it away then bury it in a moiſt place in the ground, and as that waſts the grief will waſt alſo.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:119654:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Mallows and Sengreen, beat them and boyl them in water, then ſtrain them, put oatmeal grots ſoked in Vinegar and ſheeps-ſuet untried, then boyl it to a poulteſs. Proved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Archangell red ſtamp it in a mortar with Vinegar and bind it to the place grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and if it go not away mix a little Opium with it and it will not fail.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good cooling Clyſter to apply where it needs.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pottle of running water, and Succory leaves, and Sorrill, and Strawberry leaves, and Violet leaves, and Mallows, of each one handfull, one pennyworth of French-barley, ſweet Fennell ſeed, and the four cold ſeeds of each one pennyworth, boyl all theſe to a pint, and ſtrain it, and adde one ounce of Syrup of Roſes, and a piece of butter as big as a Walnut, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:119654:56"/>
                  <head>For the Gonorrhea or Running of the Reins.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt purge the humor with new drawn Caſſia, one ounce extracted, mix therewith two drams of waſht Turpentine, and one ſcruple of <hi>pulvis athriticus</hi> into bole, then next day ſaving one diſſolve ſix drams of Confecti humach in Fumitory-water, adding two ſcruples of <hi>pulvis Sanctus,</hi> and half a dram of Cream tartar, mix them, and after the body is thus purged, uſe reſtringing Medicines.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a Gunſhot if there be a Flux of blood.</head>
                  <p>TAke Bolearmoniack one ounce and <hi>terra ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galatum</hi> one dram, and myrrh one dram pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verized fine, and a dram of <hi>Vitriolum album</hi> or white Copras, and this will be a ſtringum pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, mix with this the white of egges, and make it as it were an ungent, and ſo uſe it two daies and then undreſs.</p>
                  <p>And then ſecondly take ſpirit <hi>revini</hi> or ſpirit of wine one ounce, and Melle roſarum half an ounce, and one dram of <hi>Aegyptiacum,</hi> mix them together and put them into a poringer, and heat them hot and dip in a pleget of lint, and ſo lay it to the wound till you ſee the wound digeſted, or that the wound be cleared, and after
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119654:57"/> it is digeſted, uſe to incarnate or breed fleſh, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Baſilicon</hi> warm upon a pleget of lint, and that is ſigitriſing of the wound.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a Fracture in the Scull or wound in the Head.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſpirit Revinum and Melle roſarum, heal and dip a pleget of lint and ſo lay on the wound, but if the perecranium ly bare mix in ſome mire aloes, of each about a ſcruple among the other medicines, or if the wound be on any part of the body, uſe the ſame intention if the bone lie bare do the ſame as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A good Medicine to deſtroy Heat in the Face, or any other place, although is be S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     </hi> Anthonies <hi>fire.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke a pottle of Smiths water, and a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Sage, Elder leaves two handfuls, or the green bark thereof, Allum two pennyworth, ſeeth all theſe together from a pottle to a pint, then take it and put it into a Gallypot, and let the Patient when he goes to bed anoint his face therewith, and the next morning he will finde eaſe, it will help him five or ſix daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:119654:57"/>
                  <head>Headach or Megrim, the cure, or a good cool water to be uſed for the Head if it be over hot, or for any ſuch diſtemper.</head>
                  <p>TAke Violet leaves, red Roſe leaves, Letice and Willow leaves, of each two handfuls, and a little Henbane, Vinegar, white Poppey, and a little Mandrake, and diſtill them together in a Stillitory, and ſo keep this water cloſe ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in a glaſs untill you have occaſion to waſh your head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent hot water for the Head, if it be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cold, or any ſuch diſtemper.</head>
                  <p>TAke Bettony, Camomill, Rue, Savery, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyroyall, Marjerum, Origanum, Fennell, and Elnacampana, of each a like quantity, and diſtill them alſo, and uſe it as the former.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a pain in the Head.</head>
                  <p>TAke a Roſe-cake and cut it fit to lay to your forehead, and wet it well in Vinegar, and put thereto a good quantity of the powder of Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs and the powder of Cloves, and let the ſame be bound very hard to the temples of the Patient, and this will ſpeedily help him.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:119654:58"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke the juice of Rue and put into the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthrils of the Patient and it will expell fleam, cleanſe the brains, and mitigate the pain of the head, and this hearb ſodden in Wine will do the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another to purge the Head.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Pellitory of <hi>Spain</hi> and chew the root thereof in your mouth four or five daies at ſeveral times, and this will take away the pain of the head and faſten your teeth and gums.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For winde in the Head.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good handfull of the flowers of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momill, and half a handfull of the powder of Cinamon, mingle them together, and make two little bags of the breadth of your ears, and put both the powder and the flowers therein, and bind it cloſe to both your ears. This <hi>Prob. est.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For Heart-burning.</head>
                  <p>TAke five or ſix corns of good Pepper and bruiſe them in your mouth and let them go down your throat. This will help forthwith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:119654:58"/>
                  <head>Hoarſneſs, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke three or four Figs and cut them in the middle aſunder, and then put into every one of them a pritty quantity of Ginger fine beaten to powder, and then roſt them upon a clean hearth or upon a tileſtone, and let the Patient eat them as hot as he can endure them. This hath cured ſome which have been troubled with hoarſneſs four or five years.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Headach of rheume, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke one Nutmeg, Cubebs, Piony ſeed, Setwell roots, Marjerum, Angellica roots; of each two drams, dry them and powder them fine, and make them up with Honey into a maſe for Pils, take thereof five ſmall ones every morning for fourteen daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the ſame, Approved.</head>
                  <p>TAke four ounces of gray ſope and bray there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the whites of two egges, and put it in a box, and when you have uſe for it ſpread it on a cloth double, and lay it to the forehead, even to the ears, dreſs it ſo twice a day for five daies, you will finde eaſe at twice dreſſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:119654:59"/>
                  <head>Megrime, pain or winde in the Head, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke a piece of Methridate as big as a good hazel nut, and put it in your mouth, and let it there melt without chawing, holding your breath as much as you can, and as it melts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it into your ſtomack. This will be preſent help.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, or for any Impoſthume or Feaver in the Head.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke the roots of Pellitory of <hi>Spain</hi> one dram, Spicknard half a dram, beat them together, and boyl them in good Vinegar, then let them cool, put thereto honey and muſtard, of each a ſawcer full, mix them together, and let the Patient put half a ſpoonfull thereof in his mouth, and hold it there a while, then ſpit it forth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new it ſo twelve times, when you go to bed drink a little down, uſe it three daies and you will be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Lice or Scabs in childrens Heads, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke red Sage chop it ſmall and boyl it in freſh butter with Pepper powdered, when it is ſo boyled together, ſtrain it and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:119654:59"/>
                  <head>A good Medicine for the black Jaundies.</head>
                  <p>TAke the Gall of a Raven and dry it well and beat it to powder, then take a pritty quantity thereof and temper it either with Ale or Beer, and let the Patient drink thereof every morning faſting for ſix or ſeven daies together and it will preſently help him. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke of the roots and leaves of Strawberries, and eat them every morning faſting for the ſpace of eighteen daies together. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi> The ſame made into pottage or broth and taken fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, will do the ſame either for black or yellow, eſpecially for yellow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the yellow Jaundies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a good handfull of red Nettle crops, ſeeth them well in a pint of Ale, and ſtrain it through a clean cloth, and let the Patient drink thereof firſt and laſt for four or five daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Itch.</head>
                  <p>TAke five or ſix ſpoonfuls of Barrows greaſe, and a penny-weight of quickſilver, and a
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119654:60"/> handfull of bay Salt, and ſix ſpoonfuls of faſting ſpittle, and bray them altogether untill the quickſilver be conſumed away; let the Patient anoint himſelf therewith, and it will deſtroy the Scabs. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke ſweet butter, unwrought wax, Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Brimſtone, a little Roſe-water, red Cloves whole, boyl them together till they be like a Salve and anoint your body therewith three ſundry nights and no more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Yellow Jaundies, a ſure and quick cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Plantine water one pint, Ivory powder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two drams, Saffron ſo much as will make it yellow, boyl them all two or three walms, then ſtrain it and drink a good draught morning and evening.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious Medicine to deſtroy an Imposthume in the body.</head>
                  <p>TAke Tanzy one handfull and waſh it, Maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair flowers that grow in wheat one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, bruiſe them alone, take either of their juices one ſpoonfull, mix them with three ounces
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119654:60"/> of Camomill water diſtilled, drink thereof warm very early a pritty draught, this will purge the diſeaſe downward without pain, take of the powder of Maidenhair in your ordinary broth three times a day; alſo the roots of Scabions half a pound ſtamped, and mix therewith ſome powder of Boral well together, and drink there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a draught in Camomill water three times a day and the Impoſthume will break and ſpit forth. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To ripen and maturate an Impoſthume.</head>
                  <p>TAke the roots of Mallows and Lillies, and boyl them in water till they be tender, ſtamp them with freſh Hos-greaſe and meal, and apply it hot.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To kill the Itch.</head>
                  <p>MOrtifie Quickſilver with faſting ſpittle, and mix it with as much Hogs-greaſe as will make it blackiſh, anoint the palms of your hands and the ſoales of your feet when you go to bed, and in the morning waſh it with this water,</p>
                  <p>Take Indive water and Vinegar, of each a like, Roch-allum, powder of <hi>Enula campana,</hi> boyl them together and waſh the grief therewith, and this will cure and ſtop the fluxion of blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:119654:61"/>
                  <head>Jaundies Black and Yellow, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Earth-worms, waſh them in four or five waters very clean, ſtrip all the earth out with your finger and ſtamp them ſmall, put ſtale Ale unto them and ſtamp them hard out, and drink it with Saffron, it cureth at three times.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>How to know the Kings-evil, or a Diſeaſe ſo called, and alſo the Cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke one ounce of pure yellow wax or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more, and one ounce of Turpentine, and a good quantity of ſheeps ſuet clarified and made pure, boyl all theſe together very well, and then put therein the quantity of two good handfuls of the fineſt and pureſt Barley-flower very clean without any pulce or ſeeds of any manner of weeds, temper this flower and the other things together, then put therein the quantity of three ſpoonfuls of the Urine of a male Childe being not above three years old, then boyl it again with the reſidue of the things before mentioned, then let it cool and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome Gallypot for your uſe and ſtop it cloſe, when you do uſe it take it and ſpread it upon a fine linnen cloth or a piece of leather and lay it to the grief, and this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:119654:61"/>
                  <head>You may know it certainly by this following rule.</head>
                  <p>TAke a ground-worm and lay it alive upon the place grieved, then take a green Dock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaf or two, and lay them upon the worm, and then binde the ſame about the neck of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent at night when he goes to bed, and in the morning when he riſeth take it off again, and if it be the Kings-evil the worm will be turned into powder or duſt, or elſe he will be and remain dead in his own former form.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſoveraign Medicine for the Cough of the Lungs.</head>
                  <p>TAke a handfull of Raiſins of the Sun and let them be clean waſhed and ſtoned, and a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyworth of Maidenhair, and one ſpoonfull of Anniſeeds bruiſed ſmal, ten or twelve Figs, and three quarters of a pound of <hi>Portugall</hi> Sugar, and three pints of fair running water, boyl all theſe together till half be conſumed, then ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth, and every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drink thereof two ſpoonfuls luke-warm. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:119654:62"/>
                  <head>A good Medicine for a ſore Leg that doth feſter or rankle.</head>
                  <p>TAke Smallidge roots and Southernwood, Houſeleek, and Violet-leaves and roots, and Waybroad leaves, of each a good quantity, and a good quantity of Honey, and temper it well wich the hearbs, and ſtrain them through a fine linnen cloth and make a plaiſter thereof and lay it to the ſore, and renew it twice every day, and alway before you lay on your plaiſter waſh the ſore well with white-wine or oyl of Roſes, and in time of your cure put alwaies into your drink daily two or three Sage leaves, this hath cured many. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke two white Herrings out of the pickle, and open them, and lay the inſides of them to the ſoles of your feet when you go to bed, and renew them in the morning, uſe this five or ſix times and it will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A very good drink made of whey which will cool the extream heat of the Liver and Stomack.</head>
                  <p>TAke Violet leaves, Sinckfoil, Succory, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive, Scabions and Femitory leaves, of each
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119654:62"/> a good handfull, and ſeeth them in a pottle of good whey which hath been boyled, and let it continue till the third part be conſumed, then ſtrain it through a fine cloth, and let the Patient drink a good draught thereof morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a certain time, and this will cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For any diſeaſe in the Liver.</head>
                  <p>TAke the Liver of a Hare well dried and beat into powder, and drink it in Ale or Beer or Wine, and this will do much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To preſerve the Lungs.</head>
                  <p>TAke the Lungs of a Fox and dry it well and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t it into powder, and then put a quarter of a ſpoonful thereof into Almond milk, or into Veal or Mutton broth, and let the Patient eat it, and this will mightily preſerve the Lungs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Cough of the Lungs.</head>
                  <p>TAke green Box and dry it and powder it, and ſearce it, take ſo much at once as will lie on a groat in a draught of warm white-wine morning and evening till you be well, which will be as ſoon as you ſee your ſelf avoid blood, then leave taking your Medicine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:119654:63"/>
                  <head>For heat in the Liver, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Liverwort, Maidenhair and Harts-tongue, and Scabions, and Strawberry-leaves, of each two handfuls, Egrimony and Hop buds, of each half a handfull, boyl all theſe in a gallon of wort to the conſumption of a quart, then ſtrain it and put it to the fire again with the white of an egge and one ſpoonfull of pure Honey let it boyl again, then with a ſpoon ſcum off the white of the egge and put in ſome Sugarcandy, and take it faſting till you be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A plaiſter for the diſtemper of the Liver.</head>
                  <p>TAke Oyl of Roſes two ounces, Wax three ounces, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Populion</hi> half an ounce, melt them together on the fire well mixed, then take it from the fire and put it in a mortar and adde thereto red Sanders ſteeped in Roſe-water one ſpoonfull, and Camphire prepared one dram, work all theſe together with peſtel till they be wrought together when it is cold make a plaiſter thereof and lay it on the right ſide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Liver. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:119654:63"/>
                  <head>A Leglifium for a Gunſhot.</head>
                  <p>BOyl up with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi> wort, Centory, Bayes, Wormwood and Roſemary, of each one handfull, and to a gallon of water adde a quart of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and uſe it in this manner,</p>
                  <p>As for a Fomentation heat it hot and dip red clothes of cotton into it and lay upon the wound as big as will lie on the wound or member, as hot as the Patient can endure it, and that will bring out and evacuate all that intuſed blood that is in the wound.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Cough of the Lungs or Tiſick: Proved.</head>
                  <p>TAke four ounces of double refined Sugar, and two ounces of the flower of Brimſtone, half an ounce of Gum-dragon, ſteep the Gum in Roſe-water all night, the next morning beat the Sugar very ſmall, and put the Sugar and flower of Brimſtone into the Gum-dragon and Roſewater, and work them well together till they come to a paſte, then make it into little cakes as big as a ſix pence, then put them into a pewter diſh and dry them in a window by the Sun, or by the ſhelving of the fire, and when they are ſo dry put them in Papers and lay them where they may have the ayr of the fire, eat this at your pleaſure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:119654:64"/>
                  <head>An approved Medicine for one that is molten within by travel or any other labour.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of good Claret wine and ſeeth therein a good quantity of avence, and make a poſſet with the ſame Wine, and let the Patient drink three or four times thereof warm when he goeth to bed, and it will cure him. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Morphew.</head>
                  <p>TAke Muſtard-ſeed and Salt and ſtamp them together with Vinegar, and let the Patient anoint the place where the grief is, and it will cure in a ſhort ſpace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke green Copras and put it to ſteep in fair running water, and let it remain a day and a night, and then ſtrain it through a fine cloth, and when occaſion ſerveth anoint the place often where the Morphew is, and it will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:119654:64"/>
                  <head>An excellent Medicine for a woman troubled with the Mother.</head>
                  <p>TAke Lovage and Eliſanders, of them an ounce, roots and leaves of Smallidge, one ounce, and of the roots of Buglaſs, Bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ge and Parſley, Fennell, and Succory, of each of them one ounce, of Maidenhair, Harts-tongue, wilde thyme, and wilde marjerum, of each of them 2 ounces, of Cummin ſeed, Coriander ſeed, Carroway ſeed, Smallidge ſeed, and Dill ſeed, of them 3 ſpoonfuls, and a good quantity of Raiſins of the Sun, and bray them altogether and ſteep them in white-wine or ale for the ſpace of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four hours together, and then ſtrain them and let the Patient drink this firſt and laſt for a certain ſpace, this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a ſharp humour in the Matrix after a miſcarriage.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of poſſet-ale, boyl therein Motherwort, Mugwort, Mother of thyme, Camomill, of each one handfull, mader-root one ounce, boyl theſe together till half be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and cloſe covered, be ſure when it is boyled put in a pint of white-wine and drink a porrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger full night and morning ſo ſoon as the Patient
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119654:65"/> hath miſcarried, and this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent remedy for a Canker in the Mouth.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of red Sage and twelve crops of Roſemary, and a like quantity of Honey-ſuckles, white Daſies and Sinkfoyl, and boyl them altogether in a pint of fair water un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be half conſumed, then take a little Roch-allum and burn it to powder, put half a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Honey therein, and then ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth, and when it is cold put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome glaſs or earthen thing that it may be ſtopped cloſe, and let the Patient waſh his mouth therewith, and it will cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To increaſe Milk in a womans breaſt.</head>
                  <p>TAke Cryſtall and beat it fine into powder, mingle it with as much Fennell ſeed likewiſe beaten into fine powder, and a little fine Sugar, and let the woman drink thereof often warm with a little white-wine, and this will reſtore her milk again, although it be clean gone from her. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:119654:65"/>
                  <head>An excellent good water to kill the canker and ſcurf in the Mouth.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of white-wine and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendine, red Sage, Roſemary ſtripped, and Hyſope, and Woodbine leaves, of each of them one handfull, and boyl them in white-wine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till one half be conſumed, then ſtrain it and wring forth the juice clean, and then take half an ounce of Allum, a quarter of an ounce of white Copras, and two or three ſpoonfuls of Honey, and mingle it with the juice aforeſaid, and ſet it one the fire again and let it ſeeth a little while and take it off and ſtrain it again, and then put it into a Viall, and when you will uſe it waſh the grief two or three times a day either with a fine cloth upon the end of your finger, or elſe upon a ſticks end if the place cannot be come at other waies. This hath holpen many.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame. Approved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a quantity of running water, and a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Woodbine leaves, Bramble leaves, and Colibine leaves as many, and a little Roſemary, and boyl them together till the water be half conſumed, then put in two or three ſpoonfuls of Honey, a piece of Roch allum, three or four
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119654:66"/> ſpoonfuls of Wine Vinegar, and waſh your mouth with the ſodden hearbs three or four times a day, this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For Numneſs in the Joints.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Patient drink every morning faſting one ounce of Camphire in a draught of Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony water, wherein infuſe a little Stechadoes, this will cure in a moneths time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To provoke womens Menſtrues.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſo much of the powder of Ariſtolochy <hi>rotunda,</hi> Myrrh and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>avine mixed as will he on a ſhilling in warm w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e-wine, adde thereto one race of Ginger grated.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To ſtop their much flowing.</head>
                  <p>TAke the ſhels of new laid egges, and pill off the inner filme, boyl it one hour in water and drink that powder at twice in red wine when it is dried and beaten to powder, and at every time of drinking let her go to the neweſt mole-hill and put away the earth with her foot, and ſit down on the place and make water in the hole ſo made, and during the cure let her eat Iſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs: let her uſe this till ſhe be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:119654:66"/>
                  <head>A ſingular good Oyl for all manner of bruiſes, ſpleens and ſwellings in the legs or arms.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pint of pure Sallet-oyl or ſomewhat more, and bruiſe a good quantity of Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil and put therein, &amp; then put it into a glaſs, and ſet it to ſtand in the Sun in ſome place where it may be ſafe ten or twelve daies, but at the five daies end then ſtrain it through a fine linnen cloth, and ſet it to ſtand in the Sun again the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther five daies, and then ſtrain it again and ſet it in the Sun again the third time, and let it ſtand till it be clean purged from any dregs, and then put it into a clean glaſs and ſtop it cloſe untill you have uſe for it, and when you have occaſion to uſe it, anoint the place grieved two or three times a day, chafing it before the fire, and it will help the grief. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi> This Oyl ſtopped cloſe will continue good twelve years.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſpeciall Oyl to heal bruiſes, ſwellings, wounds, and burnings, and what not.</head>
                  <p>TAke Camomill, Peniroyall, Sage-royall, or red great Sage, Southernwood, Boneſet, Setwell, Charity, Self-heal, Knotgraſs, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi> wort, and Lavender when it is blown, of each one handfull, the leaves of red Roſes one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119654:67"/> wipe all theſe in a clean cloth, cut them all at one length one inch long, lay every hearb by it ſelf in a baſon, and put thereto three pints of the beſt Oyl-olive, and half a pint of the beſt <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> of the ſecond diſtillation, ſtirre them together and cover them cloſe, and ſo let them ſtand two daies and two nights, then boyl them together with as ſoft a fire as may be five or ſix hours, then ſtrain it, and when it is cold put it up in glaſſes for your uſe. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Sciatica, Gout or Ach, an excellent Oyl to cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke Sallet-oyl one pottle, put it into a broad gallon glaſs, infuſe therein Roſemary flowers bruiſed one pound, let them ſtand in the Sun cloſe covered till Midſummer, then take red roſe buds one pound, take out the whites, Dill half a pound, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi> wort one pound and a half, Vervine half a pound, bruiſe all theſe hearbs, then put them into the glaſs of Oyl, ſtop it cloſe again, and ſet it in the Sun for ten daies more, then after a ſhower of rain gather one quart of earth-worms, cleanſe them in white-wine, and wipe them hard in a courſe linnen cloth; and take Lavender, Spike half a pound, and ten young Swallows out of the neſt, beat them ſo ſmall till you diſcern neither bones nor feathers nor guts, and then put theſe worms,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119654:67"/> oyl and ſwallows into the glaſs of oyl alſo, and ſo let it ſtand in that place again one night or more, then pour out all theſe ingredients into a pipkin and cover it cloſe, adde thereto one pint of malmſie, and half a pint of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> let theſe ſimper ſoftly till the wine and <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> be waſted, then ſtrain it hard and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a double Viall and ſtop it cloſe, boyl it in ſome Balneo with ſome powdered Cloves and Maſtick powdered, of each two drams, let them boyl half an hour ſoftly, then ſet it in the Sunne again ten daies, and then put it up and let it ſtand ten weeks before you uſe it, and then uſe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a pint of old Malmſie, and half a pound of unſalted butter out of the churn, and boyl them together till they come to be a ſalve, and anoint the grief or any other pain therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſpecial Oyl for all Aches and Bruiſes, called Nerve-oyl.</head>
                  <p>TAke Camomil, white Archangel, Plantine, young Wormwood, Mints, Waltnut tree leaves, Sage, Violet leaves, Mallows, Rue, Chickweed, Brooklime, Water-creſſes, Sovern-wood, Smallidge and young Bay-leaves, of each
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119654:68"/> one handfull, bruiſe them all in a mortar, then boyl them in a pint of white-wine cloſe covered till the wine be near waſted, then adde thereto Hogs-greaſe and Dear-ſuet, of each one pound, Linſeed oyl and Neatsfoot oyl, of each one pint, Roſin powdered ſix ounces, Galbanum prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red two ounces, boyl all theſe covered cloſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſoft fire till the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum</hi> be green, then ſtrain it out till it be hot, mix therewith liquid Storax and oyl of Spike, of each one ounce, mix and ſtirre it till it be cold, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make Oyl of Snails for any ach.</head>
                  <p>TAke in <hi>May</hi> black Snails one pint, put them in a great Ox bladder with one pint of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and let the ſubſtance of the Ox gall run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reſt, then adde oyl of Peeter two ounces, oyl of Spike two ounces, and tie up the bladder as hard as you can, and put it into another blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and hang it up faſt tied for twenty daies where neither rat nor mouſe cometh, at the end of that time ſtrain it out and keep it in a Vial for your uſe, only adde liquid Storax one ounce, for that is good and giveth a good ſent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make a good Oyntment or ſalve for any ſore.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good handfull of Sage, as much of Plantine, as much brown wort, as many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119654:68"/> ſuckles, as much Turfame, as much Valeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, boyl all theſe in <hi>May</hi> butter till it be brown, then ſtrain it and put in a good quantity of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins wax, and then boyl it again a little more and keep it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An Oyntment good for Sprain, Ach or green Wound, or old <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer: Keep a good Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter alſo upon the wound.</head>
                  <p>TAke four handfuls of Detainder, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Elder buds, and two pound of <hi>May</hi> but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Detainder and buds muſt be ſtamped together before you put them to the butter, which muſt be firſt melted in a skillet, then put in your other things, and let it ſimper upon the fire about ſix hours, then ſtrain it into a pot and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make flower of Oyntments, which cleanſeth old wounds and new, and gathers good fleſh, it helpeth headach and Impoſthumes in the head or in the body, it helpeth ſwollen ears or cheeks, or the jaw fallen in the face, it helpeth cut ſinews, and bitings of mad dogs, it helpeth pricks or ſprains in travell, it helpeth rheumes, it draweth out iron, thorns, and it helpeth all manner of botches and ſwellings, it helpeth aches in the cods or in other members, it helpeth the flux of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119654:69"/> the emrods, it is good to make a ſear-cloth for all manner of griefs, it helpeth the flux and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrues in women, being laid to the navill.</head>
                  <p>TAke Roſin and Perroſin of each a handfull and half, Virgins wax and Olibanum of each a quarter of a pound, Maſtick one ounce, Sheeps tallow a quarter of a pound, Camphire two ounces, Turpentine two ounces, make your gums into fine powder and ſearce them, melt your wax and tallow, and mix your powders well therewith and boyl them together, then ſtrain it through a canvas bag into white-wine, let it cool till it be blood warm, then adde to it your Camphire and Turpentine by little and little, ſtirring it till it be cold, and then make it into rouls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſoveraign drink to open the Pipes ſtopped.</head>
                  <p>TAke Indive, Succory, Parſley, Fennell, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radge, Hyſope, Thyme, Pennyroyall, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander and Neep, of each a good quantity, and boyl them in a pottle of fair running water, and let it boyl till half be conſumed, and then ſtrain it and adde two ſpoonfuls of good wine Vinegar, and three or four ounces of fine white Sugar to ſweeten it, and let the Patient drink every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening three daies together a good draught. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:119654:69"/>
                  <head>For the Palſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke Sage leaves, and Primroſe leaves, of each of them a like quantity, if it be in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Primroſe roots, beat them both together, and ſtrain them with Ale, and give it to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to drink a good quantity at a time, and this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For lameneſs in the ſide coming by the Palſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke Sage and Hyſope, and boyl a good quantity together in fair running water, and bathe the ſide that is grieved well therewith, then take the hearbs and binde them as hot as may be ſuffered to the place grieved, and this will help. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſoveraign drink if it be taken in time, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>TAke a dram and half of the powder called Imperial, one dram of Treakle, and Dragon water and Sorrell water, of each a dram, drink it with Ale in the morning faſting, although the party have been infected with the plague twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four hours before, yet by Gods grace he ſhall eſcape. This hath been truly proved.</p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:119654:70"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a good handfull of winter Savory and boyl it in a quart of good wine Vinegar, with a ſpoonfull of grains being beaten and put to it, and adde alſo a good quantity of fine Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and take a good draught thereof morning and evening, and if you muſt of neceſſity come into the place where any infectious perſons are, it is good to ſmell to the roots of Angellica, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian or Valerian, and likewiſe a piece of Arras root kept in your mouth as you walk, any of theſe are very good and cordial. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke an Onion and make a hole in it and take out the inner core, then take Dragon-water, Treakle and Pepper bruiſed, and put them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into the Onion, and roſt it in the embers, and then bruiſe it and ſtrain it into pure Malmſie and give it to the Patient to drink, this is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent remedy if it be given before the heart be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good plaiſter to draw the Plague-ſore to a head, and to break it.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good handfull or two of Mallows, one handfull of Linſeed, one handfull of ſower
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119654:70"/> dow, and two or three Lilly roots, and ſtamp all theſe together very ſmal and boyl them in a quart of white-wine lees untill it be thick, then lay it one inch thick or more upon a piece of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is ſomewhat broader then the ſore, and let the borders of the leather be plaiſtered with Shoemakers wax, and that will cauſe it to cleave faſt, this will break it in a ſhort ſpace. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſoveraign Medicine to cure the Pluriſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke Brooklime, Sheeps ſuet, and a little fair water, and fry them together in a fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pan, and make a plaiſter thereof and lay to the ſide of the Patient, and this will draw forth all the corruption. <hi>Prob. est.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> and Capons greaſe, of each a pritty quantity, and boyl them together, then take a little black wool and dip it therein, and lay it as hot as may be ſuffered to the grief, and this will give eaſe ſpeedily. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the French Pox, an Oyntment good.</head>
                  <p>TAke Allum, Verdigreaſe, Engliſh Honey that is good, and wine Vinegar that is both
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119654:71"/> ſtrong and ſharp, of each a like quantity, mix them well together to an Oyntment, anoint the grief therewith often and it will both dry and heal. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An excellent Receipt called</hi> Moſes <hi>water, very good for the French Pox or any other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe growing out in ſores or ſcurfs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke ſix gallons or more of the pureſt white-wine that may be gotten, and as much ſtale Ale, and a pound and half of Sarſaprila, of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coriſh and Scena, of each of them two pound, and two pound of the bark of Guyacum Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quintida four ounces, let all theſe be boyled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the ſpace of twenty four hours over a ſoft fire, and put therein with the reſt a little <hi>Backma maria,</hi> and when it is well boyled put therein one ounce of Methridatum, then take it off and put it into ſome earthen pot and ſtop it up cloſe, and when you will uſe it take a good quantity thereof at a time three times a day, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at three a clock and going to bed, and this will cleanſe both inward and outward parts of the body, and cauſe the body to be ſound after it, when that is done, make more and uſe it often. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:119654:71"/>
                  <head>For the ſmall Pox.</head>
                  <p>TAke Milk, Saffron and Engliſh honey and ſeeth them together and give it to the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and let him be kept warm, and this will bring out the diſeaſe. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent good Purge for any manner of diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke half an ounce of Senna, one ſpoonfull of Anniſeeds, half a dram of Licoriſh, one ſpoonfull of Fennell ſeeds, a few Raiſins of the Sun the ſtones picked out, boyl them together in a quart of fair running water, and let it boyl till the one half be conſumed, then ſtrain it, and adde thereto one dram and half of Diaphenicon, and ſhake the ſame well together, and let the party which deſireth to purge drink a pritty quantity thereof every morning faſting blood-warm, and it will purge him well without cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any ſickneſs. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another Purge for the ſtomack.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke young Mallows and Mercury, of each of them a good handfull or ſomewhat more, Senna one dram, and three ſpoonfuls of Anni-ſeeds, and put them into one pint of white-wine
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119654:72"/> and as much ſtrong Ale, and let them ſtand one night, the next day ſeeth them together again untill the one half be conſumed, then ſtrain it and give the Patient a good draught thereof in the morning faſting, and if he ſleep a little after it, it will be never the worſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another Purge for all parts of the body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke two drams of pure Turpentine, and waſh it very well in Fennell water, and bruiſe it and diſſolve it in a mortar with a peſtill, and put thereto half the yeolk of a new laid egge and one dram of Smallidge water, and beat them altogether till it be like Milk, and let the Patient ſip it off, and this will work effectually in all parts of the body.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>TAke the water of Bettony and Pimpernell, and Turmentill or Scabions, mix it together and drink it nine daies faſting and fear no Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:119654:72"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Doctor</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urgeſs <hi>his Receipt againſt the Plague, and for any ſymptome of it, or the ſmall Pox or Meaſels, or for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Ague or Feaver.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke three pints of Malmſie, Sage and Herb-grace, of each one handfull, boyl them altogether till the third part be conſumed, then ſtrain it and put into it one pennyworth of long Pepper, Ginger half an ounce, a quarter of an ounce of Nutmegs, boyl them altogether a little while, beat your Ginger and Nutmegs to fine powder, adde thereto alſo two penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth of Treakle, four pennyworth of Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum, and a quarter of a pint of good Angel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica water: keep this ſecret as your life. If the party be infected take two ſpoonfuls warm, and let him ſweat well upon it; if not, one ſpoonfull every day is ſufficient, half in the morning, the other at night, this never failed any that took it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Pluriſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke a fair Pippin, cut off the top and take out the core, and fill it half full of the powder of Olibanum, and then lay on the top again and roaſt it leiſurely upon the embers, ſee it do not burn, and when it is enough roaſted cut it in
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119654:73"/> four parts with the Olibanum in it, and give it to the Patient to eat, and it will ſuddenly cauſe the Impoſthume to break, and it will cleanſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make Oyl of Puppy, which is good for any ſtrain or bruiſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke a fat Spannell puppy, if you can get one, but let it be what puppy it will it muſt be fat, and dreſs him as you dreſs a pig, then take half a doſe of yeolks of egges, and two handfuls of Roman nettles cut very ſmall, three ounces of <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, and three penny-worth of Saffron, and beat them altogether, and put them into the belly of the Puppy, and ſow it up and roaſt it, and what droppeth from it ſave, and it will become perfect oyl for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer uſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Poultis that will break a ſore in twenty four hours.</head>
                  <p>TAke black-berry leaves and Muſtard ſeed, and beat them together till it be a Poultis. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:119654:73"/>
                  <head>A Preparative to take before a Purgation, the night before it is taken, the doſe is one dram in Diaprunis or poſſet-ale.</head>
                  <p>TAke Senna; Turbith, Diagredii, of each three drams, Epithimum, Galingal, of each one dram, Salt gem ſix grains, all fine ſearced and mixed and taken as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Purgation which purgeth all aqueous humours.</head>
                  <p>TAke Rewbard, Turbith, Hermodactils, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agredii, Senna, Agarick, Mechoacan, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, of each two drams, Cloves, Fennell, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Anniſeed, Maſtick, of each one dram, Saffron and Cinamon, of each two ſcruples, ſearce all theſe, the doſe is one dram in Succory water or Poſſet-ale.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make Pils that purge the four humours.</head>
                  <p>TAke Mirabolaus and Rewbard, of each four drams, the juice of Egrimony and Worm-wood, of each two ounces, Hermodactils, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grick, Coloquintida, Aloes, of each ſix drams, Maſtick, red Roſe leaves, Salt, gem, Epithimum, Annis and Ginger, of each one dram, ſearce them and mix them, and compound them in a mortar
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119654:74"/> with ſyrup of Roſes to a maſe for Pils, the doſe is one dram in five Pils taken in the pap of a roaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed apple.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Pils of excellent vertue to purge all Flegmatick Feavers or Agues.</head>
                  <p>TAke Agarick, Aloes, Acorus, Turbith, of each one dram, Eſula half a dram, Coloquin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tida one grain, Salt gem, Maſtick, Ginger, Wormwood, Lettice, Raiſins mundified, Bdelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, of each three drams, let ſyrup of Roſes be made up with theſe Pils, the doſe is two drams more or leſs according to the ſtrength of the Patient; if you adde theſe following they are good in <hi>tertian</hi> Agues, Rubard two drams, Spicknard half a dram, Diagredii, Maſtick, of each one dram, mix theſe with thoſe aforeſaid, the doſe is half a dram more or leſs, according to the ſtrength of the Patient and the vehemency of the Feaver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Purgation that cleanſeth the head, brain and all the body of Melancholly.</head>
                  <p>TAke Senna ſix drams, Ginger one ounce, Bugloſs one dram, flowers thereof two drams, infuſe all in a cloſe ſtopped ale-bottle of ſtone, with a pint of whey of Goats milk, boyl them in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119654:74"/> Balnea one hour, and let it cool when it is boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, warm it in the morning and give it the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and it preſerveth againſt all paſſions of the brain, it alſo helps hearing, ſmelling and ſeeing, and ſtrengtheneth all the body, and doth unburthen the body of all humours that abound, as choller, fleam and melancholly, this was the practice of <hi>Mathiolus Riolanus</hi> and <hi>Achaius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Palſie.</head>
                  <p>TAke Roſemary, Sage, Herbmandlin, of each a handfull, Camomil-flowers three hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, and with Sallet-oyl make oyl thereof, as you make oyl of Roſes, and anoint the grieved parts therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Purgations with Senna.</head>
                  <p>TAke Senna in ſome quantity, with ſome Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in your broath, for the pain of the head four drams may be given to children and to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with childe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent for the Piles.</head>
                  <p>BOyl in freſh butter Pilewort and Elder leaves or buds till it be a Salve, make it yellow with Saffron and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:119654:75"/>
                  <head>An excellent healing and cooling Plaiſter.</head>
                  <p>TAke Wax and Deer ſuet, of each four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Lapis Caluminaris two ounces, <hi>May</hi> butter two ounces, Camphire one dram, Oyl of Roſes eight ounces, mix them and melt them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and make your liquid Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Plaiſter of Adders-tongue and ſweet Maud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, all green, which cureth green wounds and old ulcers.</head>
                  <p>TAke Linſeed oyl one pint, Adders-tongue and ſweet Maudline, both green in <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June,</hi> of each three handfuls, ſtrip forth their ſtalks and bruiſe them, then boyl them in the Oyl, adde thereto white-wine, let them all boyl till the herbs be very ſoft, then ſtrain them out and put the liquor to the fire again, adde thereto Roſin and Wax bruiſed eight ounces, boyl them till all be melted, ſtill ſtirring it, then take it off preſently, mix therewith <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine ſix ounces, liquid Storax one ounce, and ſo it is made.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A gentle Purge for Melancholly, and to comfort the ſpirits.</head>
                  <p>TAke the juice of old Pippins, and Burradge water, of each as much as will make a draught,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119654:75"/> heat it ſeething hot, then infuſe therein all night Senna four drams, Manna and ſyrup of Roſes, of each one ounce, Anniſeed bruiſed four drams, next morning ſtrain it and drink it warm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Rickets, a diſeaſe common to Children.</head>
                  <p>TAke Egremony, Scabions, Coltsfoot, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nill, Tamaris, of each one handfull, one pennyworth of Maidenhair, a ſmal handfull of unſet Hyſop, ſix tops of Spermint, ſix leaves of Harts-tongue, a little Liverwort, and opening roots, as Fennell, Parſley, Succory, Spergrace, ſcrape them clean and take the pith out of them, ſprinkle them with wine Vinegar when you have ſo done, ſlice them, and about half an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter put them to the reſt of the herbs, and adde licoriſh half an ounce, Anniſeed a quarter of an ounce, Raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, and Currants, and Figs, of each two ounces, boyl all theſe in a pottle of running water untill it come to a quart, and let the childe drink thereof twice a day morning and evening conſtant, and for a time at four a clock in the afternoon, if the child be hot you may boyl in it two ounces of French barley.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Beer for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>TAke Tamaris two handfuls, Brooklime and Scurvy-graſs, and Watercreſſes, of each four
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119654:76"/> handfuls, Egrimony, Scabions, Bettony of the wood, of each two handfuls, Aſh-bark, and Ivy-bark, of each two ounces, and half an ounce of Anniſeed, Licoriſh one ounce, boyl all theſe in four gallons of wort till half be conſumed, and let the child drink of this at any time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a quarter of an ounce of Licoriſh, as much Anniſeed, a quarter of a pound of Raiſins, five Figges, one pennyworth of blew Currants, Coltsfoot, Calemint, Fennell roots, Parſley roots, Marygold flowers, Tamaris, Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litory of the wall, Liverwort, Lungwort, of each a handfull, boyl all theſe in a pottle of running water to a quart, and uſe to give it the child fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and at night, and to anoint the body uſe <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum de dolfe,</hi> anoint the back bone, belly and left ſide and breaſt at night going to bed, and have a care of the childe catching cold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Pils of great vertue for the running of the Reins.</head>
                  <p>TAke Bole, <hi>Terra ſigilata, Sanguis Draconis,</hi> of each one dram, Conſerves of red Roſes three ounces, make it up into a maſh for Pils, the doſe is the quantity of a Nutmeg morning and evening.</p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:119654:76"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>FIrſt purge well with new drawn Caſſia one ounce in a draught of white-wine, and then take Pearl, Coral, Creſſes ſeed and Mader, of each four ounces, Comfry roots dried and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and Acorns powdered the cups of them, of each of them four drams, make all theſe with <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine into a maſh for Pils, the doſe ſeven Pils as big as a pea morning and evening.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another preſent help for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Oatmeal, and beat it very ſmall, and put it into a quart of new milk and ſeeth it, and put therein a good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Sugar, and when it is well boyled ſtrain it and give it the Patient to eat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a conſumption in the Reins.</head>
                  <p>TAke a handfull or two of Clary leaves and prick them, and four or five yeolks of Hen egges newly laid, and take Saffron and dry it upon a little ſtone or ſome ſuch thing, and grind it very ſmall, and put all theſe together and fry them in freſh butter, and let the Patient eat of this faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:119654:77"/>
                  <head>A Medicine againſt the Stone in the back or blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or for the weakneſs of the back, which is called the Reins running.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine and waſh it in Roſe-water, either red or damask, untill it look white, then divide it into ſmall bals, as you may eaſily ſwallow, the full quantity of three bazel nuts, then roul them in Sugar to make them the more eaſie, then ſwallow them in the morning faſting, and faſt three or four hours after them, take theſe three or four ſeveral mornings and in your water will appear much gravel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Medicine to provoke Sleep to the Sick.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of womens breaſt milk, and put thereto as much in quantity of <hi>Aqua vilae,</hi> ſtir them well together, and moiſten the temples of the head, and the noſthrils of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient well therewith with a fine cloth or feather, and it will do them much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good drawing Salve.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Roſin bruiſed ſmall, and a pritty quantity of good Wax, and a good quantity of Honey, mingle them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119654:77"/> and ſet the ſame upon a ſoft fire, ſtill ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it till it be melted into a perfect Salve.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a Stitch in the ſide.</head>
                  <p>TAke Acorns and dry them and beat them into fine powder, and mingle that powder with a little powder of Cinamon and Ginger, and give it the party grieved to drink in Ale, Wine or Beer, and this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke Sage and Burnet, of each a like quantity, and dry them upon a tileſtone, and make the ſame into fine powder and give it to the Patient to drink in Beer or Ale at meals and at other times for the ſpace of three or four daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and this will cure. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Sciatica.</head>
                  <p>TAke Ivy, Mugwort, Walwort, and the inner rind of an Elder-tree, and ſeeth them in fair water with a good quantity of Salt, and bathe the ſore place well therewith for nine daies together three or four times a day, and this will cure.</p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:119654:78"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a pint of Neatsfoot-oyl, a pint of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and a handfull of roaſted Onions, and ſtamp them together and then ſtrain them, and it will be an Oyl, anoint well the place grieved morning and evening before a good fire as hot as you can ſuffer it, and chafe it well. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To provoke Sleep.</head>
                  <p>TAke the ſeeds of Lettice and Smallidg, of each a like quantity, and make a powder thereof, and put the ſame into a quantity of white-wine, and give it to the Patient lukewarm, and it will cauſe him to ſleep preſently. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Bettony and ſeeth it in either Wine, Ale or Beer it will do much good, it is alſo good for the milt and liver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A pretious water for the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>TAke Balm, Turpentine, Scabions, Bettony and Pimpernel, of each a good quantity, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill them together, and let the Patient drink
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119654:78"/> often of this water, and this will help him; it is alſo good againſt the Peſtilence, and for thoſe that are troubled with the Mother, and for the marrow of the bones, and for to comfort the Liver. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Salve to draw and heal.</head>
                  <p>TAke half a pound of Turpentine, a quarter of a pound of Roſin, as much Bees wax as Roſin, and adde as much Hogs ſuet or <hi>May</hi> butter as will make it ſoft, which is about two ounces. This is approved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Medicine approved for the Spleen.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of Claret wine, a pint of Oyl-olive, two good handfuls of Camomill ſhred ſmall, boyl theſe together till half be conſumed, and with this anoint the hardneſs of the Spleen morning and evening, and it will diſſolve.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For one that Speaks in his ſleep.</head>
                  <p>TAke Southernwood and lay it in white-wine, and let the Patient drink thereof morning and evening.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:119654:79"/>
                  <head>For the Sciatica.</head>
                  <p>TAke the gall of a Bull, and a quart of wort, boyl it to a pint, then put in a pint of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, powder of Frankincenſe one ounce, Honey half a pound, of Commin in powder half a pound, boyl them together till they be thick, and ſpread it upon leather, apply it hot, lay a linnen cloth between the skin and the Plaiſter, the Plaiſter will ſerve many times. Proved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For all manner of ſores, old or new: Called The gift of God.</head>
                  <p>TAke Bettony, Vervin, Pimpernell, Bugloſs, Smallidge, Plantine, Scabions, Egrimony, of each a like quantity, ſtamp them together and boil them in a gallon of white-wine to the third part, then ſtrain them and adde to them a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Sheeps ſuer, and half a pound of wax, half a pound of Roſin, half a pound of Pitch, one pound of Olibanum, and boyl it again till by reaſon and art thou doſt think it ſufficient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent Salve or Sear cloth: Which being laid to the ſtomack will provoke Appetite, and take away the pain of the ſtomack: Being laid to the belly it will cure the Cholick: Being laid
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119654:79"/> to the reins of the back helpeth the running of the reins. It is alſo good for the bloody flux, and for the heat of the kidneys, and weakneſs of the back. It healeth all ſwellings of the breaſt, and taketh away all Impoſthumes, or any aches. It breaketh all ſwelling puſtils. It draweth away all running ulters, not breaking skin. It being applied to the fundament it healeth all defects there. And being applied to the head it helpeth all pains there and of the eyes.</head>
                  <p>TAke four pound of Oyl-olive of the beſt, red lead and white lead, of each one pound, and twelve ounces of Spaniſh ſope, incorporate all theſe well together in a good glazed earthen pot over a ſoft fire the ſpace of one hour and half, untill the matter be turned ſomething darker then the Oyl was by nature, let it boyl till that by dropping it upon a trencher it will neither cleave to the trencher, nor to your fingers then it is enough, then take ſome long linnen clothes about eight fingers long and dip them therein, and when they begin to be cold, ſmooth them upon a Table with a ſlick-ſtone and keep them for your uſe, they will keep twenty years, the older the better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:119654:80"/>
                  <head>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Harris <hi>her black Salve, good for any ſprain or ſwelling.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke of Wax three quarters of a pound, a pint of good Sallet-oyl, melt them on a ſoft fire, and then take them off the fire, and adde to it white lead half a pound finely beaten and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, then ſet it on the fire again and let it boyl half an hour, then take it from the fire again, and adde to it Frankincenſe, Maſtick the fineſt, drops of Olibanum, of each two ounces, and alſo Myrrh two ounces, beat them all fine and ſearce them and put them in, and ſet it on the fire again, let them boyl half an hour more, then put in half a quarter of an ounce of Camphire, and let it boyl till it be black, be alway ſtirring it, then take it from the fire, and ſtirre it till it be cold, and keep it for your uſe. It is good al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for any wound. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another rare Sear-cloth for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a quart of pure ſweet Oyl and one pound of red lead very finely beaten, boyl it in a bel-mettle skillet, upon a ſoft charcoal fire about half an hour, ſtirring it with a wooden ſtick, then dip a piece of linnen cloth in it and cool it, if it ſtick not to your fingers then it is
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119654:80"/> enough, then dip in linnen clothes into it and hang them upon a pack thread in the ſhadow untill they be dry, then lay papers between eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſheet, and ſo keep it for your uſe. <hi>Approved.</hi> Anoint the grief with that Oyntment wherein is Detainder four handfuls, <hi>page</hi> 119. before you apply the Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To cure a Strain in the arm in a ſhort time.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſome Wormwood and freſh butter and mix them together, and anoint the grief therewith, and bind the arm well, and in a day or two it will cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make a Balſom that will cure all manner of Sores or green wounds, the beſt that ever was.</head>
                  <p>TAke two ounces of <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, beat it in Roſe water and Spring water together three or four times till it look white, then take two ounces of Virgins wax cut ſmall, boyl them together in a pint of Canary Sack, let it boyl half an hour, then take it off and put in half an ounce of red Sanders beaten ſmall, ſo it is made.</p>
                  <p>The juice of an Onion will take away a Scald.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:119654:81"/>
                  <head>For a Stitch.</head>
                  <p>TAke a dry Acorn, beat it to powder, and as much Treackle as a hazel nut, mix them together, and give them to the Patient in a quantity of white wine going to bed, and it will help.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good Pill to cauſe Sleep and eaſe pain.</head>
                  <p>TAke Cinamon, <hi>Caſſia ligna,</hi> Opium, of each two drams, Myrrh, and both the Peppers one dram, Caſtory half a dram, Saffron one ſcruple fine powdered and made to a maſh for Pils, the doſe two Pils no bigger then a ſmall tare.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To break a Stone.</head>
                  <p>TAke the ſhell or thin rinde of Acorns, the hips of a briar, red holy briars and Nutmegs, all dried and powdered, drink thereof morning and evening in white-wine half a ſpoonfull at once for ſix daies or more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For all Sickneſs, Feavers, Impoſthumes or any other diſeaſe in mans body.</head>
                  <p>TAke Hyſop, Bettony, Roſemary, Violets, Vervine, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi> wort, Avence, Mouſ-ear,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119654:81"/> Plantine, Feverfew, of each one handfull waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed clean and ſtamped in a mortar, put them in a clean earthen pot which is new, with a gallon of white-wine, let it ſtand cloſe covered to infuſe all night, in the morning boyl it cloſe covered to the conſumption of half, then ſtrain it through a hair ſive into a double viall, and let the ſick drink thereof morning and evening a good draught, and this powder following is to be taken therewith.</p>
                  <p>Take Gallingall and Nutmegs, of each four drams, Ginger one ounce, Cloves, Cinamon, of each two drams, Licoriſh ſix ounces, Sugar four ounces, all powdered and ſearced, mix one ſpoonfull of this powder with one pint of the liquor aforeſaid, take firſt the ſimple liquor ſix daies and ſix nights, then other four daies and nights uſe this powder with it, and this with Gods bleſſing will cure you, if ever you be cured.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To help any hurt in the Skull.</head>
                  <p>TAke the juice of Pimpernell, and wet therein pieces of linnen cloth, and apply it often to the grief, and it will ſoon cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:119654:82"/>
                  <head>To help ſhrunk Sinews, or hard ach in them.</head>
                  <p>TAke Oyl of Roſes four drams, Spermaciti one ounce, melt them together and anoint the grief therewith twice every day, then lay on alſo plaiſter-wiſe, clothes wet, butter, wax and <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> uſe this till you be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A drink to be made in the ſpring for the green Sickneſs or any other grief.</head>
                  <p>TAke Senna ſix ounces, Wormwood, Balm, of each two handfuls, Anniſeed and Fennel ſeed, of each three ounces, the juice of Scurvy-graſs three pints, Water-creſſes and Brooklime, of each a pint, bruiſe all theſe and tie them up in a linnen cloth with a ſtone to ſink it, put it into four gallons of new Ale out of the tun, and let them work together till it be four daies old, then drink thereof in the morning faſting half a pint, and if it do not purge you three or four ſtools a day, take as much at night, uſe it till you be well.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>Scurvy the cure. Firſt a Purge.</head>
                  <p>TAke Senna, Alexandrum, of each four drams, Epithimum two drams, Raiſins of the Sun
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119654:82"/> ſton'd one ounce, Fennell ſeed, Anniſeed and Ginger, of each half a dram, infuſe them all night in warm whey pritty hot, in the morning wring it out hard, and give it to the Patient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A drink to take after it.</head>
                  <p>TAke Scurvy-graſs and Devils-bit, Water-creſſes and Brooklime, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Wormwood half a handfull, ſtamp and ſtrain them and take a quart of white-wine allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a pint of water, boyl them altogether ſix or ſeven walms, adde to them in the boyling white Ginger powdered two drams, Elna Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana one dram, a little Saffron powdered, drink thereof firſt and laſt, at meals infuſe therein Saxifrage.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For the green Sickneſs.</head>
                  <p>TAke a handfull of Cowſlip-flowers, dry them and beat them to powder, and let the Patient drink one ſpoonfull of this powder in ſix or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſpoonfuls of Malmſie fourteen mornings faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Swelling, the cure.</head>
                  <p>TAke <hi>May</hi> butter and wax a like quantity, boyl them together with a little <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:119654:83"/> dip double clothes therein, and lay it to the grief very hot, and it will draw out the water and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſwage the ſwelling. Proved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Dianthos which will help all feebleneſs of the body, the tiſick, the grief of the heart and of the Liver after long Sickneſs.</head>
                  <p>TAke Cloves, Gallingall, Ginger, Spike, Nut-megs, of each two drams and a half, Cara-way, Anniſeed, Cardamonium, of each two drams, Licoriſh, red Roſes, Violets and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary-flowers, of each four drams, Honey clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and Roſe-water a pritty quantity, let thoſe things which be to be powdered be beaten very fine and ſearced, then mix them with the Honey and Roſewater, and let it ſimper on the fire to a Confection, the doſe is three drams, uſe this as a ſecret. <hi>Prob. est.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A powder for Winde and Spleen.</head>
                  <p>TAke the rind of an Orenge, Coliander ſeed, Caraway ſeed, Anniſeed, Fennell ſeed, and Parſley ſeed, of each one ſpoonfull, dry all theſe and beat them to powder, and ſearce it, then mix them with fine Sugar, take thereof in the morning faſting, at noon before dinner and after dinner, and before ſupper and after ſupper
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119654:83"/> going to bed, in a little Anniſeed water, and you will finde much good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A rare Sear-cloth or Plaiſter for a ſore breaſt, or any other ſore, or ſprain, or ach, which I have often had experience of.</head>
                  <p>TAke half a pound of Virgins wax, and half a pint of Oyl of Roſes, and half a pint of Oyl-olive, melt them altogether upon a ſoft fire of Char-coal, then let it cool in a pan till it be half cold, then take half a pound of white-lead, and beat it fine, and put it into the Oyl aboveſaid and to the wax, and ſtirre them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether on the fire, and cauſe them ſoftly to boyl half an hour, then take two ounces of Frankincenſe, and two ounces of Myrrh, and two ounces of Gum, Olibanum, and two ounces of Maſtick, beat them to powder very fine and put them into the aboveſaid Oyl and Wax, and cauſe them to boyl another half hour, ſtil ſtirring it till it be black, then adde a quarter of an ounce of Camphire, when you have taken it from the fire, ſo dip in your clothes for ſear-cloths, or work it up for plaiſters for your uſe. Proved often for what is aboveſaid.</p>
                  <p>A white toſt ſteeped in white-wine Vinegar applied to a ſtrain, is a ſpeedy remedy for that grief.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:119654:84"/>
                  <head>For the Tooth-ach.</head>
                  <p>TAke a piece of the root of Crowfoot, and put it into the hollow tooth if there be any, if none be hollow, apply it often to the tooth that aketh, and that will cure.</p>
                  <p>Again, take the powder of red Corall, put it into the tooth that akes, and it will ſoon fall out.</p>
                  <p>Again, Take Organy that grows cloſe to the ground and taſtes like <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> bruiſe it and lay it to the tooth.</p>
                  <p>Alſo bruiſe <hi>burſa paſtoris</hi> and do the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To make Teeth white, and to faſten the Gums, and to comfort the roots, and to make the breath ſweet.</head>
                  <p>TAke Vinegar of Squils and dip a piece of lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth into it, and rub the teeth and gums therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For Lues Venera, or French-Pox.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt prepare the body with purgations, as this <hi>Pulvis Arthreticus,</hi> the doſe is one dram, augment as you ſee good, not exceeding above a dram and half, but a dram and a quarter is a good doſe, or a dram of that and half a dram of Jallop.</p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:119654:84"/>
                  <p> And then uſe this Diet-drink with <hi>Lignum vitae,</hi> for every pint of water an ounce of <hi>Lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vitae,</hi> and put in ſome <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> let them drink half a pint at a time morning and evening, let their diet be chicken or ſuch meat.</p>
                  <p>And then next uſe Turbith Mellerares, begin at three grains, uſe it to a dram but no further, till you make a Salavation or Flux at the mouth.</p>
                  <p>And then make a lotion for the mouth, to waſh that daily, let the Salavation continue three weeks or a moneth, till you be ſure the ulcer be clean.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To ſtay Vomiting.</head>
                  <p>TAke Mints, Shepheards purſe, Plantine, and Knotgraſs, and Comfry, of each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſhred them ſmall and boyl them in a quart of red Wine or Claret, drink of this Wine, and plaiſter the herbs to the ſtomack in a double cloth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Vomit for any diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke and Elder bough and ſcrape off all the outmoſt rind clean, then take ſome of the inſide rind and ſtamp it and ſtrain it into ſtrong Ale which is old, and drink it lukewarm, this will ſoon cauſe the Patient to vomit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:119654:85"/>
                  <head>To ſtay Vomiting.</head>
                  <p>TAke Mints, Shepheards-purſe and Comfry, of each one handfull chopped ſmall, boyl them in a quart of red Wine or Claret, drink of the Wine, and lay the herbs plaiſter-wiſe to the ſtomack in a double cloth. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To force one to make Water which is ſtept in Sickneſs.</head>
                  <p>INfuſe and mix ten drops of oyl of Juniper in two ounces of Parſley water and drink it blood-warm, it will cure at once or twice ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Water to inject or ſerindge into the ſecrets of men or women.</head>
                  <p>TAke water and white-wine, of each one quart, Woodbine leaves and flowers, of each two handfuls, Sage, Roſemary, and Water-creſſes, of each half a handfull cut ſmall, boyl all theſe together half an hour, then put in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum powdered four drams, and two ſmall ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of honey, and boyl them about two walms, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:119654:85"/>
                  <head>To cauſe one to make Water.</head>
                  <p>TAke Saffron in powder, and pure ball ſope, as much of one as another, mingle it toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſpread it upon the fleſhy ſide of white lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, make thereof plaiſters and lay upon the navill of the Patient, and give him to drink as much of the powder of the herb golden rod as will lie on a ſix pence in a glaſsfull of Reniſh wine or white-wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An excellent ſalve for a deep Wound or cut, which requireth tenting.</head>
                  <p>TAke the yeolk of a new laid egge and honey the quantity of a Wallnut, the ſame quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of pure Turpentine, beat them altogether, and lay them to the wound with fine lint, and this will cure it in a ſhort ſpace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for a green Wound.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke wheat-flower and milk, and temper them well together, ſeeth them till they be thick, then take the white of a new laid egge, and beat it well with the aforeſaid ſtuff and it will keep it from rankling and heal it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:119654:86"/>
                  <head>An excellent Medicine for a green Wound, being applied plaiſter-wiſe, or to make a ſear-cloth for any Ach, and it is good to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken inwardly upon the point of a knife for the Lungs.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of Ale and two pennyworth of freſh butter, one pennyworth of good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, boyl all together till half be waſted, keep it cloſe covered while it is boyling. Uſe this as a treaſure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another plaiſter for a green Wound, or for a Wound that is over-healed and ſore underneath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke a good quantity of Barly-meal, and the white of an egge and honey, and mingle them well together, and lay it plaiſter-wiſe to the wound, and it will cure immediatly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For one that is brought low in ſickneſs.</head>
                  <p>TAke Egrimony, Bettony, red Sage, Fennell roots the inſide, Liverwort, Indive and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cory, of each of theſe one handfull, boyl them in four pints of milk till half be conſumed, then ſtrain it and let the Patient drink a quarter of a pint at a time morning and evening lukewarm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:119654:86"/>
                  <head>For Weakneſs in the back.</head>
                  <p>TAke Clary, Dates, the pith of an Ox, Cream and Egges, and bread grated, mingle them all together, and fry them, mix with them white Sanders, ſtrew Sugar upon them, and give it to the Patient faſting in the morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A ſalve for a green Wound.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pound of Roſin, half a pound of Wax, four ounces of old Swines greaſe, one ounce of Verdigreaſe, boyl them all together upon a ſoft fire, and ſtrain them for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A good remedy for one that cannot make Water.</head>
                  <p>TAke three or four hive Bees, kill them and dry them upon a hot ſlate, then bruiſe them to fine powder, then put the powder into a quart of Ale and give to the Patient a pritty quantity at a time. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>To heal Wounds and ſores, and alſo to draw.</head>
                  <p>TAke Roſin, Frankincenſe, of each four ounces, white wax and Olibanum, of each three ounces, Harts-ſuet and Maſtick, of each
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119654:87"/> one ounce, <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine half an ounce, white-wine a pint, melt the Roſin, Frankincenſe and Suet together, then ſtrain it into a pan, and adde to it then the white Wax, the Olibanum, and the Maſtick powdered, and the Wine, then boyl all together till the Wine be conſumed, then take it from the fire and ſtirre it till it be almoſt cold, then put in the Turpentine and make it up in a roul, and keep it in parchment or leather.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Water to heal all ſores and ulcers.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pound of Roch-allum, four ounces of green Copras, beat them and ſet them on the fire untill they be melted, then let them dry again, then beat them into fine powder, then ſet a pottle of ſpring-water over the fire till it boyleth faſt, then take it off, and when it ceaſeth boyling, caſt your powder abroad on the water ſo long as the water ſhall riſe, till it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear black in the bottom, then it is perfect, wherein dip a cloth and lay it double to the ulcer or wound, firſt laying on the wound ſome of the powder and roul it up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A Medicine to kill all manner of Worms in the body.</head>
                  <p>TAke Plantine leaves and roots, and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, of each a like quantity ſtamp and ſtrain
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:119654:87"/> it, and give it the Patient to drink mixed with a pint of good Malmſie warm together, give this to the Patient for the ſpace of three or four daies together, and this will kill worms in the maw or elſewhere.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Another for the ſame, which will ſpeedily kill the Worms.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TAke <hi>Aqua Compoſita</hi> that is made of herbs, and waſh the Patients breaſt therewith, then take a little powder of myrrh, and beat it very ſmall and ſearce it fine, and ſtrew that alſo upon the breaſt after it hath been well waſhed, and then lay on a warm cloth upon the breaſt and ſet it remain twenty four hours together. This hath been proved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For Winde and ſhooting in the head.</head>
                  <p>TAke Egrimony and Cinamon, bray them and put them in Ale, and lay it it to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of your head, and as the pain removes, ſo remove your medicine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>An unguent to heal a green Wound at the firſt dreſſing.</head>
                  <p>TAke Aloes ſiccatrine fine powdered, and the powder of perroſin, of each a like quantity,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:119654:88"/> mix them and grind them with the white of an egge, and lay it on a pleget of lint, and apply to the wound.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>A plaiſter to cure and heal a Wound.</head>
                  <p>TAke Letherage of Gold one pound, Oyl of Roſes two pound, white-wine Vinegar and old Urine, of each half a pound, let them boyl till the Vinegar and Urine be conſumed, adde to it in the boyling Wax two ounces, Frankincenſe one ounce, mix it well and apply it. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="medicine">
                  <head>For a Woman in Travell.</head>
                  <p>TAke a Date-ſtone and grate it into fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and give it the Patient with white-wine, and God willing ſhe ſhall be dclivered without danger. <hi>Prob. eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>Thus have I diſcharged my Conſcience to my Countrey, not hiding any thing from them which hath been imparted unto me. I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you the generall Method of Phyſick and Chyrurgery, with three hundred rare Receipts ſuitable for to cure any Diſeaſe incident to the body of man, which ſecrets have moſt of them been kept from the ſight of the world, ſtill to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:119654:88"/> keep creatures in blindneſs, and to advance their own intereſt, which in this Treatiſe I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to take off: and that the poor may not periſh for want of help by reaſon of their pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, here is a Garden to which they may go, and cure any Diſeaſe curable, with ſmall coſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="printers_advertisment">
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THeſe Books following are Printed and ſold by</hi> Simon Miller <hi>at the Star in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> Pauls <hi>Church-yard, near the Weſt end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Harmony, Chronicle and Order of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> By <hi>J. Lightfoot</hi> D. D. In <hi>fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Civil Warres of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Emperour of <hi>Germany.</hi> Wherein our late unhappy differences are parallel'd in many particulars: In <hi>fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith, or the Good old Religion, By <hi>Jo. Nicholis</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel: In 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Bolton</hi>'s Generall Directions for a Comfortable walking with God: In 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Anatomy of Mortality. By <hi>G. Strood:</hi> In 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Ainſworth</hi> on the <hi>Canticles:</hi> In 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Paul Baynes</hi> Dioceſans Triall: In 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Supream Power of Chriſtian States, Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated from the Inſolent pretences of <hi>Gulielmus Apollonii:</hi> By <hi>E. Gralle.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119654:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Several Politique and Military Obſervations of the Civil &amp; Military <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> By <hi>D. P.</hi> Eſq;.</p>
            <p>The Meritor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us Price of Chriſts R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>demption: By <hi>W. Pinchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>New-England.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>Aſtrology Theologi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: In 4<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jo. Lilburn</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Trial at <hi>Guild-Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Reconcile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 8<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ed. Waterhouſe</hi> Eſq his Diſcourſe of the <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> of Elder Churches and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. 8<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>An Antidote againſt <hi>Popery:</hi> By <hi>Peter du Moulin.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>A ſhort View and Defence of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by K. <hi>Edw.</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>The Poor mans <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgion.</hi> In 8<hi rend="sup">0</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Book of Schemes or Figures of Heaven, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſet for every 4 minutes of Time.</p>
            <p>Rudiments of the Hebrew Tongue: By <hi>H. Knoales.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robinſons</hi> Eſſaies: In 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>The duty of Children to Parents: In 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſſelius</hi>'s Apothegmes: 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>A Compleat Practice of Phyſick: By D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>J. Smith.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">0</hi>.</p>
            <p>The New Teſtament. 24.</p>
            <p>The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> part of the Bible. 24.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
